music
music
applause
applause
Today's meeting was supposed to be hosted by the vice president of our Humanities Society
今天這個會本來是應該由我們的人文社會的副院長來主持
But it just so happens that he is not here today because of a pharmacist, and even the vice presidents are very busy, so there is no way
但是碰巧他因為有藥工今天不在 連底這個幾個副院長都很忙 沒有辦法
So I had to be represented by Quan Cong, and I would like to say sorry to the host
所以只好由我權聰來代理這個會 對這個主持人說聲抱歉
Today's keynote speaker is Director Hu Xiaozhen. He is the director of the Institute of Culture and Philosophy and is currently a researcher of the Institute.
今天的主講人胡小鎮所長 他是文哲所的所長 也是目前文哲所的研究員
Everyone will know after listening to his speech that he is very knowledgeable, so I am also very happy to have this opportunity today
大家等一下聽他演講就知道 非常有學問 所以我也很高興今天有這個機會
Enjoy this voice of his literary novel
享受這個他的文學小說的聲音
Director Hu is a PM from the Wanwen Department of National Taiwan University and a master of literature from De Yaguo, California.
胡所長是台大萬文系PM 加州省德亞國的文學系碩士
Dean of East Asian Civilizations at Harvard University
哈佛大學的東亞文明學院長
A Ph.D. with Mingxi Wu
與吳明希的一個博士
Works and other students
著作等生
numerous awards
得獎無數
In 1999, he won the Young Works Award of our middle school
1999年就拿到我們中院的年輕著作獎
Awarded by the National Science Council in 2003
2003年拿到國科會的
Wu Great Excellence Award
吳大優獎
This is very difficult in academia
這個都是在學術界非常難
An award for young scholars
拿到的一個給年輕學者的一個獎項
that 2012
那2012年
Also got the special book on humanities and society from our middle school
也拿到我們中院人文社會專書的
First Book Award
第一屆的專書獎
so visible
所以可見
He has a lot of heart on his body
他這個身上帶的心臟是很多
His main research
那他主要的研究
Mainly in the literature and art of Ming and Qing Dynasties
主要是在明清的文藝學
and this
還有這個
Especially in the subject of the main prize for women's literature he's waiting for
尤其在於女性文學他等一下的主獎的一個題目
he this
他這個
Published several books
發表了好幾篇專書
I'm not here
我在這邊就不
a fastest
一個最速
That
那
The topic of his speech today will be the master. Wait until everyone sees him.
今天他演講的題目就成主等一下大家看到他一樣
Chai girl, Chai girl, Chai girl and the like
柴女 柴女 柴女之類到柴女不妹
His raised head is very appropriate to himself
他的抬頭跟他本人是非常的貼切
It mainly focuses on the emotion and imagination of women's novels in the Qing Dynasty
主要是聚焦在清代女性小說的情感與想像
Now, all distinguished guests, please welcome our Director Hu Xiaosheng
現在就請各位貴賓歡迎我們的胡小聲所長
Thanks
謝謝
Peng Ding long
彭定書長
Dear friends inside and outside the hospital
在場的各位院內外的朋友們
I am Hu Xiaozhen from Literary Institute
我是文者所的胡小珍
It is a great honor to be invited to the knowledge feast of our Academia Sinica today
今天非常榮幸受邀到我們中研院的知識饗宴
Let me share with you some of my research experience
來跟大家分享我的一些研究心得
In fact, there are studies on women's literature in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
事實上有關於明清時代女性文學的研究
not my new research
並不是我的新的研究
Or Wu Ning said she was my earlier actor
或者吳寧說她是我比較早期的演員
But I think sometimes it's a new era
但是我覺得有的時候就說到了新的時代
Can exchange for a new meaning
可以換發出新的意義
I do research on this
我從事這方面的研究
Actually from the 90s
事實上是從90年代開始的
but since the 90s
但是從在90年代
and my related book published in 2003
以及我的相關的專書在2003年發表的
in the process
在這個過程當中
I think the acceptance of women's literature and women's issues
我覺得關於女性文學以及女性問題的接受度
In fact, it is far from being as high as everyone's concern about related issues now.
其實遠不如現在大家對相關問題的關切度那麼的高
So I want to bring this topic back here
所以我想重新把這個題目帶到這裡
Come and enjoy with everyone
來跟大家一起來欣賞
let's feel together
一起來感受
Let's criticize together
一起來批評
Maybe it still has new meaning
或許仍舊是有新的意義的
So today's topic
那麼今天的這個題目
I don't know what you think when you see the title
我不知道各位看到題目的時候有什麼想法
So from talented women to talented women who are not beautiful
那麼從才女之類到才女不美
Talented girls are already so tired
才女都已經那麼累了
why don't you say
為什麼還不說
go to bed
去睡觉呢
why doesn't he want to sleep
他为什么不想睡觉
or why can't sleep
或者是为什么睡不着呢
in fact
事实上
this here
这里的这个
Words like rich girl
财女之类的这个类字
not what we usually say
并不是我们平常说的
oh so tired
哎呀好累啊
Very sleepy
好困啊
so tired
好疲劳啊
The class that really wants to sleep
好想睡觉啊的那个类
what about this class
这个类呢
I actually borrowed one
其实我是借用了一个
American sinologist
美国汉学家
Called Ronald Egan
叫做Ronald Egan
Professor Ellen Knoll
艾朗诺尔教授
to the Song Dynasty
他对宋代的
famous female writer
著名的女文学家
Li Qingzhao's research
李清照的研究
What about his original text?
那么他的原文呢
is called
是叫做
The Burden
The Burden
one attached to him
一个附加在他身上
something he didn't want
他本来不想要的东西
So
那么
The Sinologist pointed out
這位漢學家他指出
that's not what i said
這不是我說的
It's what Professor Elonor thinks
是愛朗諾教授他認為的
He said that in traditional society
他說在傳統的社會
Literary sanctions for women are a major
女性的文藝制裁是一個重大
why
為什麼呢
Because male literati intellectuals
因為男性的文人知識分子
scholars, officials, etc.
學者 官員等等
the entire mainstream society
整個的主流社會
talented for women
對於女性有才
And put it on the creation of literature and art
而且把它放到文藝的創作上面
this thing is not satisfactory
這件事情是不太滿意的
is biased
是有偏見的
They believe that women should not engage in literary and artistic creation
他們認為女性不應當從事文藝的創作
Then the male literati are against such behavior
那麼男性的文人對這樣的行為是
is suppressed
是打壓的
And what's worse than creating it is
而且比創作這件事情更糟糕的是
Spread the good work
把創作好的作品流傳出去
because for the ancients
因為對於古人來說
A woman's handwriting is like a part of her
女性的手筆就好像是她的一部分一樣
So for a person who should not put himself
所以對於一個不應該把自己
a woman exposed to public society
暴露在公眾社會的一個女性
If the work is exposed to the eyes of the public
如果把作品暴露在眾人的眼前
that is also an exposure
那也是一種暴露
So this public literary work
所以這種公開的文藝作品
It's actually an inappropriate behavior
其實是不應當的一種行為
Then under the constraints of this society
那麼受到這種社會的制約
the woman writer herself
這個女作家自己
no matter how well she writes
不管她寫得多好
no matter how lonely she was
不管她多麼的孤方自小
She has no way to feel at ease
她都沒有辦法去安心的
spread your work
把自己的作品流傳出去
So most authors will choose
所以呢多數的作者會選擇
take her work
把她的作品
burn it
寫完就燒掉
Or destroy her all before she dies
或者是在死前把她全部都毀棄掉
This will ensure
這樣才能夠確保
she is an innocent
她是一個清白的
pure, respectable
真潔的受人尊敬的
this elite woman
這個菁英的女性
then such thoughts
那麼這樣的想法
It is completely different from our modern people
跟我們現代人是完全不一樣的
so what
所以呢
The Song Dynasty was not without women's writing
宋代並不是沒有女性寫作
But none of their works have been well circulated.
但是他們的作品都沒有得到很好的流傳
Then Professor Alan Rowe pointed out
那麼艾朗羅教授就指出
Li Qingzhao is here
李清照就是在這
Among the many women who can write
眾多的能夠寫作的女性當中
the most special one
最特別的一位
Because he not only insisted on creating
因為他不但堅持創作
And he's not shy
而且他完全不忌諱
even hard
甚至是努力的
spread your work
把自己的作品流傳出去
And he also tried hard to shape himself into a
而且他還把自己努力的塑造成
a man of letters
一個跟男性文人
Can sit on an equal footing
可以平起平坐這樣的一個地位
so as of today
所以到今天為止
The Li Qing Dynasty is still at the top of the history of Chinese literature
李清朝都還是中國文學史上面
almost the only one
幾乎是唯一一個
a woman writer with classic status
具有經典地位的一個女作家
how to prove it
怎麼證明呢
I don't know everyone
不知道各位
We often read news reports
我們常常看新聞報導
about a few months ago
大概幾個月之前
Dean Liao
本院的廖院長
when in the legislature
在立法院的時候
He was asked by a legislator on the spot and said
由立法委員當場問他說
May I ask Dean Liao if you can
請問廖院長您能夠
Can you recite a few classical poems?
背出幾首古典詩詞呢
I think Secretary-General Peng must still remember
我想彭秘書長一定還記得
So what did Dean Liao say?
結果廖院長說什麼呀
Dean Liao blurted out that
廖院長脫口而出的就是
oh look for secrets
哦 尋尋秘密
desolate
冷冷清清
Qiqi miserable
七七慘慘
seven seven
七七
Right? Whose work is this?
對吧?這是誰的作品?
This is Li Qingzhao's "Sound Man" in the
這就是李清照的《聲聲漫》當中的
This is of course a drama
這個當然是明劇
Then it can be proved that
那麼由此可以證明
even after a thousand years
即使在一千多年之後
For the leader of an academic hall
對於一個學術殿堂的首領來說
This Ming opera by Li Qingzhao
這個李清照的明劇
Still one of the most classic words in his mind
仍就是他心目中最經典的詞句之一
It can be seen that Li Qingzhao, a female author,
由此可見李清照這位女性作者
A special place in the history of Chinese literature
在中國文學史上面的一個特殊的地位
But it is also because Li Qingzhao
但是也正是因為李清照
His literary reputation is so great
他的文藝名聲這麼的大
So this real Li Qingzhao
所以這個真實的李清照
What kind of a woman is that?
到底是怎麼樣的一位女性呢?
His face became blurred instead.
他的面貌反而就模糊掉了
will be shaded and distorted
會受到遮蔽以及扭曲
How to say it? For example
怎麼說呢?比方說
Where's Li Qingzhao?
李清照呢
Everyone knows that his husband is called Zhao Mingcheng
大家知道他的丈夫叫做趙明成
The two of them are very knowledgeable couple
他們兩個人是非常知新的一對伴侶
They are very emotional
他們感情非常的深厚
But Zhao Mingcheng unfortunately died in the middle age
但是趙明成不幸在中年曲
after death
去世了之後呢
Li Qingzhao has nothing to rely on
李清照他無所依靠
he actually made a decision
他其實做了一個決定
He remarried
就是他改嫁了
he remarried
他再婚了
Then he not only remarried
那麼他不但再婚
Moreover, within a short period of time, he
而且呢他在很短的時間之內呢
found he couldn't stand this second husband
發現他沒有辦法忍受這個第二任的丈夫
So he went to sue the second husband
所以呢他就去告這個第二任的丈夫
Said that he had all kinds of illegal situations
說他有種種的這個不法的情勢
constant behavior etc.
不斷的行為等等
And in the end, if you win this lawsuit, you will be able to get a divorce.
而且呢最後打贏了這個官司呢就得以離婚
So what about such a life experience?
那麼這樣的一個人生經歷呢
It was very illegal for the people at the time.
對於當時的人來說呢是非常的不合規範的
The first one is that remarriage itself may be stigmatized
第一個呢改嫁本身呢可能就會被污名化
The second one immediately filed a lawsuit after remarrying and said they wanted a divorce.
第二個呢改嫁之後馬上就打官司說要離婚
This may also be on the social news page today
這個在今天可能也會上社會新聞版
Then let alone sending a loan
那麼更不要說是在送貸了
So for a long, long time
所以呢在很長很長的一段時間裡面呢
Li Qingzhao's life experience
李清照的這一段人生經歷呢
Everyone doesn't know how to face him
大家都不知道該怎麼去面對他
Then some people started this harsh criticism
那麼有一些人呢就開始這個嚴厲的批評
This is called nonsense
這個叫做以人廢言
That is to say, this lady Li Qingzhao
就是說李清照這位女士
so unruly
如此的不守輔道
It can be seen that there is no need to read her works
可見她的作品也不必看了
this is a way of saying
這是一種說法
Another way is to reverse
另外一種就是要反過來
Maybe it's because I love her work so much.
可能是因為太喜愛她的作品了
So especially during the Qing Dynasty
所以特別是在清朝的時候
There are other scholars and literati
有另外一些學者文人
I tried my best to excuse Li Qingzhao
就努力的要替李清照開脫
To say that the previous stories are all false
要說以前的故事都是假的
Li Qingzhao didn't change the price at all
李清照根本就沒有改價
He always loves Zhao Mingcheng alone
他始終心理者愛著趙明成一個人
It's for him to keep the truth and cleanliness till the end
是為他守真守潔到最後的
Only in this way can he be a pure and innocent talented woman
這樣他才能夠以一個清清白白的才女
such an identity
這樣的一個身份
Such an image was handed down to later generations
這樣的一個形象流傳到後世
Then we see that no matter the former
那麼我們看到不管是前一種
Or the latter understanding of Li Qingzhao
或者是後一種對於李清照的認識
There may be a considerable distance from the real Li Qingzhao
可能都跟真實的李清照有相當大的距離
Then we until the twentieth century
那麼我們直到二十世紀
Only then did I have the opportunity to take Li Qingzhao's body
才開始有機會把李清照身上
Those heavy shackles that we have given
被我們賦予的那些重重的枷鎖
The so-called Burden
所謂的Burden
slowly remove
慢慢的撥除
let's meet
讓我們面面
This one can see Lu Qingzhao's real face
這個可以看到呂清照這個真正的一個面貌
We now see Lu Qingzhao
我們現在看到呂清照
It is a real attempt to
它是一個真正能夠試圖
To break through the mainstream society of the Song Dynasty
去衝破宋代的這個主流社會
Some Expectations and Limitations for Your Woman
對於你女性的一些期待以及限制
it can hold on to creation
它可以堅持創作
And try hard to spread its works
而且努力的去傳佈它的作品
And it doesn't just write
而且它也並不是只寫
Searching for secrets deserted
尋尋秘密冷冷清清
Qiqi residual seven seven
七七殘殘七七
not just write
也不是只會寫
Walking with the book wind last night
昨夜與書風走
sleepless nights
濃睡不消殘酒
Exam Questionnaire Confused
試問卷連人卻道
Begonia is still
海棠依舊
Do you know
知否知否
Because it is green, fat, red and thin
因是綠肥紅瘦
right
對不對
Such a work that expresses personal and private emotions
這樣一個表達個人的私人的情感性的作品
Although moving
雖然動人
but can't
但是並不能
All on behalf of Li Qingzhao
代表李清照的全部
Well, this Professor Elano
那麼這位愛朗奧教授
He specifically mentioned
他就特別提出來
for example
比方說
This Li Qingzhao wrote a lot
這個李清照他寫了不少
to reflect on history
去反思歷史
even to respond
甚至去回應
Works of the current situation in the great era
大時代的時局的作品
For example, he has a poem that says
例如他有一首詩說
life valentines day
生當作人節
death is ghost
死亦為鬼雄
So far, I have been thinking about refusing to cross Jiangdong
至今思向於不肯過江東
He said
他說
to this person
向於這個人
Born as a dragon and phoenix among human beings
生的時候是人中的龍鳳
Even if you die, you are still a hero among ghosts
就算死也是鬼中的英雄
Although some people say
雖然有人說
towards the time of defeat
向於戰敗的時候
Some people say you run away
有人說你趕快逃走吧
If you escape to Jiangdong, you can temporarily save your life
逃到江東就可以暫時保住一命
aftereffect
以徒這個後效
But Xiang Yu said he would rather
但是向於卻說他寧可
Never want to be a waste of time
一死也不肯做個渦浪費
refused to cross Jiangdong
不肯過江東
refused to flee to Jiangdong
不肯逃到江東去
So
那麼
Compared with what Li Qingzhao faced at that time
對照於當時李清照所面對的
Northern Song Army City
北宋軍城
The scene of hurriedly fleeing all the way to the south
匆匆的一路昌皇的逃到南方去的情景
Of course we can imagine the poem
我們當然可以想像這首詩作
In fact, it is entrusted to Li Qingzhao
其實寄託著李清兆
Li Qingzhao's view on the male-dominated society of the Northern Song Dynasty
李清兆對於男性所主導的北宋社會
and dissatisfaction with the political situation
以及政治情勢的不滿之意
Then also through these big historical perspectives
那麼也通過這些具有大的歷史觀照
and reflective works on politics and society
以及政治與社會的反思的作品
Li Qingzhao did win over
李清兆他確實就爭取到了
The position of literati who can sit on an equal footing with male literati
可以跟男性文人平起平坐的文人的位置
Okay, so far, I should actually be helping you read.
好 到這裡為止我其實應該算是幫大家讀書
A general summary and description of recent years
大致的總結以及說明了最近這些年來
Whether it is Chinese literature or not
不管是中文學界也好
Or the Western Sinology circles
或者是西方的漢學界也好
Some New Viewpoints on Li Qingzhao's Problem in the Song Dynasty
對於宋代的李清兆的問題所做的一些新的看法
then i guess this
那麼我猜想這個
You might like to watch a short video of this
大家可能會願意看一小段這個影音
very troublesome for you
非常麻煩你
This section is from Taiwan
這一段是台灣的這個
Guo Gongliang Culture and Education Foundation
郭公亮文教基金會
A Jinkun play that just ended
剛剛才公演結束的一齣金昆戲
The so-called Jin Kun is on this stage
所謂金昆就是這個舞台上面
Some roles sing golden operas
有的角色唱金戲
Some bloody singing this kunqu opera
有的血色唱這個昆曲
Then this play is called "Qing Hui Lang Zhao"
那麼這齣戲叫做《清徽朗兆》
It describes the relationship between Li Qingzhao and his two husbands
它描寫的就是李清兆跟他的前後兩任丈夫的關係
Of course the first husband was a spy.
當然跟第一個丈夫就是間諜情深
With the second husband is the complete wish
跟第二個丈夫就是徹底的是願偶
Then obviously we can see
那麼很明顯的我們可以看到
What about contemporary opera?
當代的戲曲呢
Make a big fuss about Li Qingzhao's two marriages
在李清兆的兩次婚姻上面去大作文章
trying to drag this traditional
試圖去為他拖去這個傳統的
Really knot the burden of women's morality
真結婦女婦德的這個包袱
But let's look at this first
不過我們先來看看這一段
After we read it, maybe we can think
我們看了之後或許可以想
So in the interpretation of modern people, whether we
那麼在現代人的解讀當中是否我們
We gave another woman like Li Qizhao
我們又給李其兆這樣一個女性
Added a new burden
又加上了新的包袱呢
Let's see what this passage actually is
我們來看一下這段其實是
An official introduction to the play
這齣戲的一個官方版的介紹
only 30 seconds
只有30秒
Okay, it's over, so I don't know if any of you guys are going to see this play.
好 結束了 那麼我不知道各位有沒有人去看這齣戲啊
But we can see from this short introduction
但是我們從這個短短的介紹裡面看見
Li Qingzhao actually has a new Birden, right?
李清照的身上其實有了一個新的Birden 對不對
He is now burdened with a modern divorced woman
他現在要背負了一個為現代的失婚婦女
A classical image of what happened
發生的一個古典的形象
is this a new
這算不算是一個新的
burden?
包袱呢
In my opinion it must be
在我看來肯定是啦
good
好
I want to do it again, maybe I have a lot of friends
我想再做搞不好有不少的朋友
It's actually for Li Qingzhao
其實是為了李清照來的
I was deceived by the name of that rich girl or something.
被那個財女之類這個名字給騙了
dont know if it is like this
不知道是不是這樣
But what?
不過呢
Li Qingzhao is just the background of our speech today
李清照只是我們今天演講的背景而已
Actually my topic today
事實上我今天的主題呢
A female writer in the Ming and Qing Dynasties, especially the Qing Dynasty
是明清時期特別是清代的女作家
and a novelist
而且是小說家
So why use Li Qingzhao who was sent to the generation as the background?
那麼為什麼要以送代的這個李清照為背景呢
That's because Li Qingzhao happened to live in this era
那是因為李清照恰好他所處的這個時代
What about the Ming and Qing Dynasties that Song Dai can tell us about?
送代可以跟我們所要講的這個明清時期呢
make a nice print
做一個很好的印照
Well, some things don't change
那麼有些事情呢是不會變的
some things have changed
有些事情呢卻變了
Compared with Li Qingzhao, a female writer in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
相較於李清照這個明清時期的女作家呢
Although their creations are also restricted by many social norms
他們的創作雖然也受到了很多社會規範的限制
But the Ming and Qing Dynasties
但是明清時期
Minsei era female writer
民青時期的女作家
Their creative desires are more developed
他們的創作慾望更為發達
less malicious
更為不可惡意
Then their works spread far and wide
那麼他們的作品也流傳得更廣更遠
and male literati
而且男性的文人
For women to engage in creative work
對於女性從事創作這件事情
attitude changed
態度改變了
Many of them are very supportive
他們很多人都是非常的支持的
Then one more important thing is
那麼還有一點很重要的就是
Minsei era female writer
民青時期的女作家
they form a group
他們會形成一種群體
Whether it's a group in the family
不管是家族裡面的群體也好
in the same area
同一個地域裡面的
Groups in the same area are also good
同一個地區裡面的群體也好
Groups in the same division are also good
同一個師門裡面的群體也好
or sometimes
或者有的時候
just by text
僅僅是通過文字
A spiritual group is also good
一個心靈上面的群體也好
This feeling of being a female writer
這種同為女作家的這種感受
It was very strong during the Minqing period
在民青時期是非常強烈
and very important
而且非常重要的
Then the women writers of this period
那麼這個時期的女作家
some of them are wholehearted
他們有一些是會全心全意的
to invest in creation
去投入創作
and proud of it
而且以此為榮
Will emphasize what kind of waste you are, please forget to eat
會強調自己是怎麼樣的廢請忘食
Well, of course, this responds to the second half of the title of my speech.
那當然這就回應到了我的演講題目的後半
Talented women are not beautiful
才女不美
don't sleep in order to create
為了創作而不睡覺
then we need to know
那麼我們要知道
Ability to stay awake for a job you love
能夠為了一件喜愛的工作而不睡覺
it's actually a right
這其實是一個權利
It's actually not tiring
這其實是不累的一件事
I don't know if you feel this way
我不知道大家有沒有這個感覺
I think many women working in Academia Sinica feel this way
我想在中研院工作的很多的女性都有這個感覺
Because I like this job, I don’t sleep or get tired
因為喜歡這個工作所以就不睡覺也不累了
OK
OK
Of course, I am definitely not a woman from the Qing Dynasty
當然我絕對不是說明清時期的女性
They've gotten rid of the so-called talented women and the like
他們已經擺脫了所謂的才女之類
actually the opposite
其實相反的
They have to struggle with more so-called talented women
他們要跟更多的所謂的才女之類來掙扎來奮鬥
For example, can women pursue the livelihood of the people?
比方說女性可不可以追求民生呢
It's not just bad people's livelihood. Women don't seem to be pursuing
不只是壞的民生女性好像不應該追求
probably good in those days
在那個時代可能好
People's livelihood should not necessarily be pursued
的民生也不見得應該追求喔
Because in that era, the best position for women may be to be
因為在那個時代其實女性最好的位置也許應該是要
deep in this
深處於這個
this
這個
Look inside and taste inside
內視之內要正味於內
Should not be in the public domain to shine
不應該在公眾領域去發光發熱
so
所以
Is it a legitimate thing for these female writers to face women seeking fame?
這些女作家他們真的要面對女性求名是不是一件正當的事情
Then let alone get people's livelihood
那麼更不要說得到了民生之後
He works absolutely differently on women than on men
他的作用力在女性身上跟在男性身上絕對不同
This may not have changed to this day.
這一點到今天也或許未曾改變
For example, the status of wife or mother
又比方說妻子或者是母親這樣的身份
for a woman writer
對於一個身為女作家的人
Search inside, we can't think of it
裡面搜索一下我們其實是想不出
Which novel was written by a woman
哪一個小說是女性寫的
so is it true
那麼這是真的嗎
ok then i first
好那我先
Can you sell a pass?
賣一個關子好嗎
Let's start by getting everyone back from this one after dinner
讓我們先再讓大家從剛才吃完晚飯以後的這個
Wake up in trouble
困頓當中覺醒一下
So
那麼
please see again
先請大家再來看
a video
一段影片
Please go to the next PPT first
麻煩先到下一張PPT
What I want to invite everyone to watch is the Guoguang Theater Troupe
我要請大家看的是國光劇團
sorry
對不起
What I want to invite everyone to read is a story called Meng Lijun
我要請大家看的是一個叫做孟立軍的故事
In 2017 is this year
在2017年就是今年
Spring is actually our Guoguang Theater Troupe
春天其實我們的國光劇團
just had a play called
才剛剛公演過一齣戲叫做
Secret
不能說的秘密
what is the secret
是什麼秘密
This play is actually the story of Meng Lijun
這齣戲其實就是孟立軍的故事
1993 Yayin Xiaoji by Guo Xiaozhuang
1993年亞音小集由郭小莊
starring Meng Lijun
所主演的孟立軍
then i think
那麼我想
This audience friend who may be over 40 years old
這個可能40歲以上的觀眾朋友
And the audience friends also know that Guo Xiaozhuang
而聽眾朋友還知道郭小莊
He himself is a traditional opera
他本身就是一個與傳統戲曲
against a rebel
對抗的一個叛逆分子
So the play is performed by him
所以這齣戲由他來演示
very suitable
非常的合適
He turns you to sixty-four
他給你們轉到六十四
six...six...sixty-four
六...六...六十四
six minutes and forty seconds
六分四十秒
We started figuring out from six minutes and forty seconds
我們從六分四十秒開始開始想辦法
This paragraph is about the character of Meng Lijun
这一段的是孟丽君这个角色
she is female
她是女的
she posed as a man and got citizenship
她扮成了男性而且得到了公民
is burning sun
正在得意燃阳
Appears in men's clothing and is in official uniform
以男装出现而且是穿着官服
This is of course a golden sentence
这当然是金句
This is the symbol of masculinity
这就是男性的象征
It is also a symbol of political authority
同时也是政治权威的象征
good
好
ok we see here
好我們就看到這裡
You can see this Meng Lijun
可以看到這個孟立軍
show a smug
表現出一副得意
Yang En is really full of wisdom and virtue
楊恩真的是智德意滿的樣子
OK, let's see a comparison
好那我們看一個對比
good
好
On the left is Meng Lijun who wears men's clothing this week
左邊呢就是這個禮拜男裝的孟立軍
Miss
小姐
anxiety
心不安
Air
空氣
Little Miss
小大姐
red yellow
紅色黃色
Tokai period
東海時代
red red
紅色紅色
anxiety
不安
The one on the right is the emperor
右邊的呢則是皇帝
is his boss
是他的老闆
But what about the boss?
不過這個老闆呢
I saw Meng Lijun's appearance
看出了孟立軍這個載相
Seems
好像是
so what
所以呢
Just want to quote Meng Lijun to admit his female identity
就想要引用孟立軍承認自己的女性的身份
And become the emperor's neicheng
而且變成皇帝的內丞
Well, in the end, of course, the lecherous emperor's trick did not succeed.
那麼最後當然這個好色的皇帝的詭計並沒有得逞
Meng Lijun is with his fiancé
孟立軍呢跟他的未婚夫團員了
But is this what Meng Lijun wants?
不過這是不是孟立軍想要的呢
Where is this very reluctant emperor?
這個非常不情願的皇帝呢
As a last resort, he must fulfill this Meng Lijun and his fiancée.
他在萬不得已的情況之下必須要成全這個孟立軍跟他的未婚
In fact, it is adapted from a work called Rebirth
其實是根據一個叫做再生緣的作品來改編的
Fate of Rebirth actually refers to Meng Lijun and Huangpu Shaohua
再生緣裡面其實就是說的是孟立軍跟黃浦少華
In fact, they have been married since childhood.
他們其實是從小就有婚姻之約的
The result is that Meng Lijun is so beautiful
結果因為孟立軍長得太漂亮了
So there are bad guys who want to
所以有壞人就想
to his fiancé's house
把他的未婚夫家給
framed
陷害了
In this way, you can marry Meng Lijun and go home
這樣就可以娶得孟立軍回家
Of course, this virtuous and controversial Meng Lijun would not
這個有致節有爭糙的孟立軍當然不肯囉
So he changed Nanzhuang
所以他就改變了南莊
Went to Beijing to rush for the exam and won the first prize
進京感考而且得重了壯元
Not only that, he also put the world's national
不只如此他還把這個天下國家的
Both politics and military affairs are in the hands of the emperor and his own father
政治軍事都一手掌握玩弄這個皇帝以及他自己的父親
and this fiance
還有這個未婚夫
between applause
鼓掌之間
such a story
這樣的一個故事
Then his fiancé
那麼他的這個未婚夫
In fact, I guessed that the prime minister is a woman
其實猜出了這個當朝宰相的是女性
keep wanting
不斷的想要
I begged him to resume women's clothing, but this Meng Lijun was not willing
祈求他恢復女裝但是這個孟立軍的都不願意
Because the emperor wanted to bring Meng Lijun into the harem
因為這個皇帝有心要把孟立軍納入後宮
As a last resort, Meng Lijun finally became Meng Lijun and had to return to women's clothing
不得已最後才變成孟立軍必須要回覆女裝
Then in the process
那麼在這個過程當中
Meng Lijun was not only unfair to the emperor
孟立軍不僅是對皇帝不公
Being disobedient to your father is even more disrespectful to your husband
對父親不從對丈夫更是不敬
Then this husband because he was originally
那麼這個丈夫因為本來就是
It was under his subordinates that Wu Zhuangyuan passed the exam.
是在他的手下才考中一個武壯元的
Then we know that in traditional times
那麼我們知道在傳統時代
Teachers and students are very important
師生的名份非常的重大
So so his fiancé must also respect him as a teacher
那麼所以他的未婚夫也必須尊稱他為老師
And you have to kneel down to him often, etc.
而且必須要常常的對他下跪等等
then in the novel
那麼在小說裡面
These episodes are described in great detail.
對於這一些情節都敘述得非常的詳細
but must say with joy
而必須說是帶有喜感
And there is a feeling of singing and singing
以及就是有一種歡唱凝厲的感覺
ok so you can imagine
好那麼各位可以想像
a plot device like this
像這樣的一個情節設計
In fact, it is very attractive
其實是具有很大的吸引力的
so what
所以呢
All genres are successful
各各劇種都成功
adapt this story
改編這個故事
Regardless of what we just saw
不管是我們剛才看到的
Beijing opera is also good
京劇也好
Well actually
那麼其實
Gezai Opera has also been changed
歌仔戲也改過
It's played by Ye Qing
是葉青演的
Everyone knows who Ye Qing is, right?
大家知道葉青是誰吧
ok good
OK好
Gezi Opera also has
歌仔戲也有
Then there are musicals
那麼樂劇也有
Many dramas are like this
很多劇種都這個
Adapted the story of Meng Lijun
改編過孟立軍的故事
even
甚至
sorry am i
對不起我是不是
OK I just skipped one
OK我剛才跳過了一張
even
甚至
We also saw that he still has rumors overseas
我們還看到他還有海外的流傳
can help me point to
可以幫我點到
Not the place where the manga was adapted
不是是那個漫畫改編那個地方
ok let's look at this site
好我們看看這個網站
This is clearly a Japanese site
這是很明顯一個日本的網站
On this website, he is actually selling
這個網站上面他其實是在賣
cartoon
漫畫的
Let's see this comic
那我們看看這個漫畫
what is the story
是什麼故事
new living element
新在生元
This is Japan in the 21st century
這個就是當代21世紀的日本
Comic creations based on traditional stories
根據傳統故事改編的漫畫創作
And one of the subjects he chose was in solidarity with
而他選擇的題材之一就是在聲援
we can see inside the cover
我們可以看到封面裡面
Meng Lijun this Q version
孟立軍這個Q版
This image of Meng Lijun
孟立軍的這個形象
we can all see
我們大家可以看到
Such a story of a woman disguised as a man
這樣一個女伴男裝的故事
It actually has a rather universal appeal
它其實具有一個相當普遍性的一種吸引力
Even cross-cultural still has its appeal
即使是跨文化也仍舊有其吸引力
ok, what next
好,接著呢
Back to PPT
回到PPT
next
下一張
Then let's take a look at this work
接著我們就來看看這部作品
what the hell is going on in solidarity
在聲援到底是怎麼回事
what is its origin
它到底是什麼來歷
In fact, solidarity is a very typical
其實在聲援就是一個非常典型
And a classic novel written by a woman
而且具有經典性的一個女性所創作的小說
then his works
那麼他的作品
Chen Duansheng
叫做陳端生
He was a woman born in the mid-18th century
他是18世紀中期出生的一位女性
she wrote this Regeneron
她寫的這個再生元
It's the story of Meng Lijun we just talked about
就是我們剛才說的孟立軍的故事
Chen Duansheng was born into a very famous literary family
陳端生出生於一個非常著名的文學的家族
She followed her grandfather and father as a teenager
她在少女時期就跟著她的祖父父親
Mother studies literature and art
母親學習文藝
From an early age she had to write
很小的時候她就有了要寫
regeneron idea
再生元的想法
she started writing
她就開始寫了
I will show my mother as I write
寫著寫著就會給媽媽看
Share her creative experience with her mother
跟媽媽一起共享她的創作經驗
in a year and a half
在一年半的時間裡面
She wrote 600,000 words intensively
她就密集的寫了60萬字
I wish I could write my thesis so fast
真希望我寫論文可以這麼快
She wrote 600,000 words in a year and a half
她在一年半的時間寫了60萬字
Later, because of changes in her family,
後來因為她的家族出現了變故
mother died grandpa died
母親死了 祖父死了
So she has no interest in writing any more.
所以她就沒有興致再寫下去了
This creation is interrupted
這個創作就中斷了
then he got married
然后他就结婚了
Fortunately, he gets along well with her husband.
还好他跟丈夫相处得是不错
It's like living a happy life
好像过上了幸福的美满人生
Unexpectedly, accidental inoculation came
没想到变故接种而至
His husband was involved in a science factory
他的丈夫因为被卷入了一件科厂
It's a case of cheating in the exam
就是考厂作弊的案件
We know this in traditional times
我们知道这个在传统时代
This is Shatou's big case, very serious.
这是沙头的大案 非常严重的
then his husband escaped death
那么他的丈夫逃过一死
But he was rushed into the army and exiled
但是就被冲军了 就被流放了
Poor Chen Duansheng with two children
可怜的陈端生带着两个小孩
was left at home
就被留在家里面
then he had a very, very hard life
那么他过着非常非常艰难
sad days
心酸的日子
So in his creation from Girls' Generation
所以在他的创作从少女时代
After a 14-year hiatus
中断了14年之后
Chen Duansheng is in this heart
陈端生就在这个心灵的
in great pain
极大的痛苦当中
He decided to recreate
他决定要重新以创作
as a life saver
作为一种生命的救赎
He started picking up his pen again
他又重新开始拿起笔来
Continue to finish writing the story of Rebirth
继续要写完这个再生原的故事
but unfortunately
不过很可惜
he is still
他还是
He stopped in the middle of writing
他寫到一半就停住了
Then we'll see where he parked later
那我们待会会看他停在哪里
he stopped
他停住了
Then he himself unfortunately passed away.
然后他自己也很不幸的就过世了
Then finally by other female writers
那么最后是由其他的女性的作家
Helped him finish writing the story of Meng Lijun in Regeneron
帮他写完了这个再生元孟丽君的故事
So this one we just said he wanted to rewrite
那么这个我们刚刚说他想要重新写
But I can't write in one place
但是写到一个地方写不下去
Where can I not write down?
到什么地方写不下去呢
It's exactly the Meng Lijun we saw just now
就正是我们刚才所看到的孟丽君
His identity is about to be revealed
他的身份快要曝露了
his dad
他的爸爸
his fiance and even his emperor
他的未婚夫甚至他的皇帝
all for different reasons
都在因为不同的原因
oppress him
压迫他
Hurry up and admit that you are a woman at this critical point
赶快承认自己是女性的这个关键点上
Chen Duansheng stops here
陈端生就停在这里
We can probably imagine a suffering
我们大概可以想象一个受尽的苦难
For the plight of women's lives
也对于女性生命的困境
Chen Duansheng with many reflections
有许多的反思的陈端生
How is he going to end this story?
他到底要怎么样去收束这个故事呢
is following the expectations of most readers
是隨著多半的讀者的期待
Like most dramas we have seen
就像我們所看到的多數的戲曲一樣
Make Meng Lijun happy
讓孟立軍就歡喜的
Unload the jade belt and unload the tide view
卸下玉帶卸下潮觀
Change the beautiful hair of women on the book
換上書上女性的美麗的頭髮
Put on Jinchai and put on a skirt
戴上金柴穿上裙子
change back to female
變回女性嗎
can she write like this
她能這樣寫嗎
Or Chen Duansheng in the eighteenth century
或者是在十八世紀的陳端生
He might write Meng Lijun as saying
他有可能把孟立軍寫成說
No, I definitely don't want to give up my old political life?
不 我絕對不願意放棄我原來的政治生命嗎
It seems that Chen Duansheng has no choice
似乎陳端生都沒有辦法
Choose from either
從這兩者之間做任何一個選擇
Indeed he stops here
確實他也就停在這裡
The female writer who later helped him finish writing this work
後來幫他寫完這個作品的女作家
Of course it was written with a happy ending
當然就是寫了一個大團圓的結局
What about this work by Chen Dunshen?
陳敦深的這個作品呢
Although he himself did not finish
雖然他自己沒有寫完
But in this Jiangnan area
可是在這個江南地區
In fact, it is very widespread
其實是流傳的非常廣泛
It is a situation of manuscripts, manuscripts, manuscripts, and manuscripts being circulated
是一個手本、手抄本、寫本、搞本的情況在流傳的
And his influence is very big
而且他的影響非常的大
At his time and in later generations there were many women writers
在他的同時以及後世有許許多多的女作家
respond to his work in different ways
都以不同的方式去回應他的作品
Well of course we have to stop here
那麼當然在這裡我們必須先停一下
Let's take a look at the form Chen Dunshen used to create
來看看陳敦深所用來創作的這個形式究竟是什麼
If he is writing a novel
如果說他寫的是小說的話
Why did we not know that women in the Qing Dynasty wrote novels before?
為什麼我們以前都不知道清代的女性寫小說呢
That is actually because the novels created by Chen Dunshen have a special form
那其實是因為陳敦深所創作的小說有一個特別的形式
He is a person transformed from Tan Ci's performing and rapping form.
他是一個由譚慈這種表演的、說唱的形式轉化
a dark-headed written work
而成的一個暗頭式的書面的作品
It's called Tan Ci's novel
叫做譚慈小說
Let's take a closer look
我們進一步的來看一下
so what are the words
那麼譚詞是什麼呢
Simply put, Tan Ci is popular in the Taihu Lake Basin.
譚詞簡單的說就是流行於太湖流域的
Especially Suzhou, today's Shanghai, and so on, a kind of rap art of the generation
特別是蘇州啊 今天的上海啊等等一代的一種說唱藝術
This kind of rap art is mixed
這種說唱藝術它是運散交雜的
just sing in rhyme
就是用韻文來唱
but also uses some prose to tell part of the story
但是也會用一些散文來講述故事的部分
Sanxian and pipa are used to accompany the performance
在表演的時候會用三弦 琵琶 這些弦樂器來伴奏
Then the style of Tan Ci is very delicate, soft, and even sleepy.
那麼譚詞的風格是非常的細膩 柔美 甚至可以說很殘眠的
So it is still a very popular art form today.
那麼到今天呢都仍就是一種非常受到歡迎的一種藝術形式
And Tan Ci novels are many women who love this art form
而譚詞小說呢就是許多喜愛這種藝術形式的女性
transformed into a form of writing
轉化而成的一種書寫形式
Well, maybe not everyone here has heard what Tanci is
那麼我們可能不是在場的每一位都聽過譚詞是什麼
So I took a very old route from decades ago
所以我選了一段幾十年前的一個很老的一個路線
Let everyone know what is marble
來讓大家知道什麼是彈子
wait a minute
先等一下
Let's take a look at this picture in the upper left corner
我們先看看左上角的這個畫面
This is the form of the manuscript of Tanci novels
這個就是彈詞小說的稿本的形式
These works are often in the form of manuscript transcripts
這些作品往往都會以這種稿本抄本的形式
published after a long time
流傳很久以後才出版
Then the performance form of Tanci is like
那麼彈詞的表演形式就如同
This image we see in the lower left corner
我們在左下角看到的這個畫面
There will be one person or two people
就是會有一個人或者是兩個人
Perform with a stringed instrument
拿著弦樂器來表演
But you should pay attention
不過各位要注意
In fact, in the traditional era
其實在傳統時代呢
Those who can go to the stage to perform Tanci
能夠到舞台上面去表演彈詞的
absolutely not
絕對不會是這樣
they must be men
他們一定是男的
Only men can go to the bookstore to perform
只有男性才能夠到書場上面去表演
Women can only go inside the house at most
女性最多只能夠到家裡面
to perform in a private venue
到私人的場所來表演
good
好
Then let's take a look at a short
那麼接著我們就來看一小段
this
這個
an older video
一個比較老的錄影
What about this paragraph?
這一段呢
It's a lady talking to a maid
是一個小姐跟一個丫鬟在對話
Maid ran over
丫鬟跑過來
no it's another
不是 是另外一個
The maid ran over and reported to the lady that
丫鬟跑過來報告小姐說
Your fiancé is here, go out and see
你的未婚夫來了 快出去看看吧
But what about this maid, he didn't directly say
但是這個丫鬟呢 他又不直接說
He deliberately teased this lady
他故意的去挑逗這個小姐
gossip
風言風語
This funny lady is angry and funny
這逗的這個小姐又好氣 又好笑
I'm sorry
又不好意思
So according to their conversation
那麼根據他們的對話呢
we can see the performance of this korean word
我們可以看到這個韓詞的演出
So yes, it has both dramatic tension and lingering
那麼是 既具有戲劇張力 又具有纏綿
Official Jade Flag
公式的玉旗啊
Wow
哇
you hurry up and send it again
你快快又走去寄寄它
Whoosh, go feed yourself
嗖嗖大大自己去喂喂
you go kick it
你去踢踢它
post it
寄寄它
hello it
喂喂它
stranger it
生人它
because tactics step it up
因為戰術一步步進它
Haha good area
哈哈好地區
who wants to send it
誰要寄它
nibbling
嗑嗑
say it
世事橫說它
i want without it too
我也想要沒有它
it's one of you girls here it is
它是你們一女之中的這裡啊它
I dust wash my aunt
我这 dust wash my aunt
Not many sighed loose powder
不几个叹得松松粉呢
fresh girl holes it
新鲜妹孔它
"!
"!
Then thank you for teaching me to move you
那么谢教亲子动你
Listen to individual words
分听个人话
Thank you for your teaching and forgive him
谢教至高宽他叹辈亲上喊
a parte
一得比制个一 parte
That one is more self-satisfied than he does not move tiy
那个了自得比他不动 tiy
i don't listen to her
我不听她
legs
足
choose her
选她
ditch
沟
It's not appropriate to say it's all a secret
说这全秘密不得当
the main kid
这主要的小子
you are the wind of flowers
你出花风之风
have to do
都得是弄
very nice
真好
Said it was all hard work
说这全是弄业大力
Miss threatened that you are here and I will beat you
小姐恐吓说你在这我要打你了
Miss said you want to call
小姐说你要打
Okay, then we can see this Tanci performance
好 那我們可以看到這個彈詞的演出呢
It's actually very dramatic.
其實是真的是非常具有戲劇張力
We can't imagine with our present eyes
我們不能以我們現在的眼光來想像
You're putting yourself in an eighteenth century
你要把你自己放在一個十八世紀
Women who returned to China in the depths of the 19th century
十九世紀深處深歸中的女性
if you see a show like this
如果你看到這樣的表演
you will actually be touched
你其實是會被觸動的
And it's really going to be fun, right?
而且是真的會覺得有趣的 對吧
Well, if you still remember that Dream of the Red Chamber was in the very front
那麼各位如果還記得紅樓夢在很前面的地方
Isn't Jam talking to a so-called fairy girl?
賈姆不就跟一個所謂的女仙兒在對話嗎
They invited this female performer to their home
他們請了這個女性的表演者到家裡
Are you here to perform?
你們來表演嗎
Then the fairy girl said
那麼這個女仙兒不就說
Otherwise, I will sing the story of Fengqiu Huang
那不然我來唱一齣鳳球黃的故事
remember
記得嗎
So that performance should actually be something like ours
那麼那個表演其實應該就是類似像我們這樣
I saw such a performance of Tanci
看到的這樣的彈詞的演出
So we can actually imagine
那麼所以我們其實很可以想像
At that time, there were quite a few returned women.
當時的這個有不少的歸中的女性呢
will be rewarded for seeing such a performance
會因為看到了這樣的表演而受到
Attract some of these women who are educated to write
吸引其中一些受過教育可以寫作的女性
She thought I could use this format to create a story
她就想到我可以利用這樣的形式來創作故事
We know that storytelling is actually a human instinct
我們知道其實講述故事是一種人類的本能
Especially women love to tell stories
特別是女性是特別愛講故事的
So that's how the novel of talking words came about.
那麼談詞小說就是這麼來的
And compared to the performance of talking words in the performance we just watched
而且比較起像我們剛才看的表演裡面的談詞的表演
There will be more textual parts in real talk novels
真正的談詞小說它裡面的運文的部分會更多
The design of the characters The description of the characters will be more detailed and the plot will be very complicated
人物的設計人物的描寫會更細緻情節會非常的複雜
Just like Zhang Hui’s novels like Dream of the Red Chamber and Oil Absorbent that we usually see
就跟我們一般看到的紅樓夢 吸油劑這些張回小說一樣
It must also have Zhang, Huihui, Huimei, etc., which have all the necessary conditions for novels
它也一定是有張會有回 有回目等等具有所有小說的必要的條件
The structure is also very complete
結構方面也都很完整
But it will use seven fonts
但是它就會用七字體的運文
tell stories in english
用英文來講述故事
Therefore
正因如此
So when we take the concept of the so-called novel
所以當我們把所謂的小說的概念
Fixed in the so-called vernacular Zhang Hui novels
固定在所謂白話張回小說的時候
Then there is no place for this novel
那麼談此小說就沒有它的位置了
so that's why
所以這也就是為什麼
This is what we've been taught since childhood
我們從小到大所受的這個
in the education of literature
文學的教育裡面
no one told us
沒有人告訴我們說
It turns out that women in the Qing Dynasty wrote novels
原來青代的女性是創作一種小說
called talking about this novel
叫做談此小說的
So
那麼
maybe you want to ask
也許您要問
Are there any Zhang Hui novels written by women in vernacular?
那到底有沒有女性寫白話的張回小說呢
Actually not without
其實也不是沒有
At least we know that in the second half of the nineteenth century
至少我們知道在十九世紀的後半期
There is an aristocratic woman named Gu Taiqing
就有一位貴族女性叫做顧太卿
she actually wrote a
她真的就寫過一部
The narrative book of Dream of Red Mansions is called Dream of Red Mansions
紅樓夢的敘書叫做紅樓夢影
shadow of shadow
影子的影
But this is a very special case
不過這是一個很特殊的例子
What about women writing Zhang Hui's novels?
那麼女性寫作張回小說呢
almost unique
幾乎可以說是絕無僅有
Then this Dream of the Red Chamber is probably
那麼這個紅樓夢影大概是
is a rare example
是極少的一個例子
And in contrast
而相對的呢
What about Tanci novels?
彈詞小說呢
There are quite a lot of women to create
有女性來創作的卻相當的多
You can count more than ten or twenty kinds by random counting.
隨便一數都可以數出個十幾二十種以上
then we're going to ask
那麼我們就要問了
Why Women Don't Write Zhang Hui's Novels in Vernacular
為什麼女性不寫白話的張輝小說
And choose this form of Tanci to write novels?
而選擇這種彈詞的形式來寫小說呢
Of course, there is no standard answer to this.
那當然這個是沒有標準答案的
I can only make some guesses
我只能夠提出一些猜測
So first of all what we just said
那麼首先就是我們剛才說的
Because the performance of Tanci has a kind of attraction
因為彈詞的表演具有一種吸引力
then women like to hear
那麼女性喜歡聽
Then it's natural to say
那麼自然就覺得說
I use this form to create
我用這種形式來創作
Other women may also like to watch
別的女性也可能喜歡看
right
對不對
So this could be a
所以這個可能是一個
The psychology of expecting other women to enjoy reading
預期其他的女性喜歡閱讀的這樣的一個心理
this is one of them
這是其中的
i think one of the reasons
我覺得其中一個原因
Another reason?
另外一個原因呢
Tanci itself is a kind of entertainment
則是彈詞本身是一種娛樂
it is unrefined
它是不登大雅之堂的
What about this male literati?
那麼這個男性的文人呢
for
對於
It is simply dismissive of women to write in this form
女性用這種形式來寫東西是根本不屑一顧的
That is to say, I will not read it at all.
也就是說根本不會去讀
won't go to see
不會去看的
so is that a good thing or a bad thing
那麼這是好事還是壞事
hard to say right?
難說對不對
It's a bad thing because it doesn't get more attention
是壞事因為這樣的話就沒有得到更多的人的注意
but it's a good thing
但也是好事
Because he left a lot of room for these women to run wild horses
因為他就給這些女性留下了非常大的跑野馬的空間
If we carefully read the thoughts written by these women
如果我們仔細去讀這些女性創作的談思想
say what we will see
說的話我們就會看到
This language is really when writing talk novels
這個語性真的在寫談詞小說的時候
It can get rid of many talented women and the like
是可以擺脫不少的才女之類的
many of them in other forms such as poetry
許多他們在別的形式例如詩
For example, emotions that are inconvenient to write in words
例如詞裡面所不方便寫的情感
ambivalence or even desire etc.
矛盾或甚至是慾望等等
or some really wild imagination
或者是一些真的是相當野蠻的想像
It can all be written in the form of talkative novels
都可以在談詞小說這種形式裡面寫出來
and get letters from other women
而獲得其他女性的信
Standards and norms of mainstream society that loves men without offending them
喜愛卻不冒犯男性的主流社會的標準與規範
This is another possible reason I think
這個是我覺得另外一個可能的原因
So anyway what I have to point out here is that
那麼無論如何我必須在這裡指出的是
Whether it is Li Qingzhao in the Song Dynasty or the female writers in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
不管是宋代的李清兆或者是明清時期的女作家
Or the female novelists of the Qing Dynasty like Chen Duansheng we have seen here
或者是我們在這邊看到的像陳端生這樣的清代的女小說家
Writing is a creative activity for them
寫作對她們來說都是一種創造的活動
is a way of pursuing an immortal possibility for oneself
是一種為自己去追求一個不朽的可能性的一個方式
We all know that Confucianism says that there are ways to pursue immortality in life.
我們都知道儒家說人生追求不朽有哪些方式呢
Three Immortals
三不朽
Thank you Lide for your meritorious service
感謝 立德 立功 立言
So what can we do to build morality for women?
那麼要怎麼樣才能立德對於女性來說
If the husband is not dead, he can't be robbed quickly, right?
如果丈夫沒死就不能迅劫是吧
If meritorious service cannot go to the public domain
立功如果不能夠到公眾領域去
how do you do meritorious service
你如何立功
The only thing to say is that it is locked in the defense
唯有立言是它關在規防當中
It is also possible to engage in a creative activity
也有可能去從事的一種創作活動
Then women pursue this kind of
那麼女性就是透過創作來追求這種
After you can let your own body go to ashes
可以讓自己的肉體灰飛煙滅之後
It is also possible to exist in pursuit of immortality
還有可能流存於是追求不朽的
such a way
這樣的一種方式
Well, this is a common ultimate pursuit of human beings
那麼這是一個人類的普遍的終極追求
Then the so-called talented women are not ignorant
那麼所謂才女不昧
Awareness of unwillingness to sleep
不願意睡覺的意識
It was born from such an impulse to pursue immortality.
就是從這樣一個追求不朽的衝動裡面所產生的
good
好
Then I think we might as well come together
那麼接下來我想我們就不妨一起來
Look at the text of the section inside the solidarity
看看在聲援裡面的部分的文本
So just now we introduced the author who is in solidarity
那麼剛才我們介紹了在聲援的這個作者
Chen Duansheng
叫做陳端生
then we also know
那麼我們也知道
different from current writers
跟現在的作家不同
Today's novelists, of course
現在的小說家當然要
I went everywhere to type books
到处去打书了
But the novelists of the classical age
但是古典时代的小说家
In fact, I am very conscious of what I write
其实非常的自觉自己所写作的
is an art called trail
是一种叫做小道的艺术
It's not in the hall of the big government
是不登大衙之堂的
So even male authors
所以就连男性的作者
are often reluctant to disclose their identities
也往往不愿意公开自己的身份
Well, let alone women
那么女性就更不用说了
And for Chen Duansheng
而且对于陈端生来说
He's still a sinner's wife
他还是一个罪人的太太
right
对不对
We just said his husband was exiled
我们刚刚说他的丈夫被流放了
So even though he is a comedian from a famous family
所以虽然他是出自名门的一个大家归秀
But our whole background about Chen Duansheng
但是我们对于陈端生的整个背景
Actually don't know much
其实知道的并不太多
So how do we know there is a protozoa?
那么我们怎么知道在生原尸
Written by this woman named Chen Duansheng
这个叫做陈端生的女人所写的呢
He will never be like a modern writer
他绝对不会像现代的作家一样
He mentioned his name on the fertilizer industry
在肥业上面大大的提下自己的名字的
how did you do it
怎么做到的呢
how do we know
我们怎么知道的呢
That's because the author
那正是因为这个作者
He will use a form of speech
他会利用谈词的一种形式
And at the beginning of each chapter
而在每一张每一回的开头
or
或者是
Going to write a long paragraph at the end has nothing to do with the storyline
結尾去寫下一大段跟故事情節沒有關係
But with his own current feeling
可是跟他本人的當下的感覺
or seasons or circumstances or experiences
或者是季節或者是環境或者是經歷
Or words related to his mood
或者是他的心情有關係的文字
Then we can see from this paragraph
那麼我們從這一段就可以看到
This paragraph is the beginning of volume 17
這一段是第17卷的開頭
Volume 17 is exactly what Chen Duansheng wrote in his
第17卷正是陳端生在他的寫作
14 years off
終斷了14年
After he has gone through all kinds of hardships in life
在他經歷了種種人生的困苦之後
the volume that started writing again
重新開始寫作的那一卷
Let's see him at the beginning of this volume
那我們看看他在這一卷的開頭
how to describe yourself
怎麼樣來描述自己
Then please read the text on the PPT directly
那麼請各位直接看PPT上面的文字
then he said
那麼他說
What about him
他呢
Shaking my head to ask God
騷著自己的頭要問天啊
Why is the law of heaven so unfair?
為什麼天道如此的不公平呢
ask the sky
問天
he is here
他在這裡呢
In fact, it is a rhetoric that follows Chu Ci Tianwen from afar
其實是遠追楚詞天問的一個修詞
Yeah
是嗎
express a
表達一種對於
a sorrow of life
人生的一種悲憤之情
He said I've grown out of all the troubles in the world
他說我已經長盡了這世上種種的苦處
So I miss returning to the center even more
所以我更懷念歸中
when young
幼小的時候
that carefree era
那毫無憂無慮的那個時代
what did he do at that time
那個時代他做什麼呢
He said me and my sister
他說我跟我的姊妹呢
sleep together
睡在一起
Let's listen to the sound of rain at night
晚上呢一起聽下雨的聲音
Mom and Dad teach us to do our homework
爸爸媽媽呢教我們做功課
teach us how to make poetry
教我們怎麼做詩
This is what parents teach their daughters to write poetry
這一點父母親教女兒做詩
This is the cultivation of talented women in Ming and Qing Dynasties
這是明清才女養成裡面
a very common situation
一個非常普遍的情況
In other words, although they don't necessarily go to school
換句話說雖然他們不見得上學堂
But they can learn from family education
但是他們可以從家庭教育裡面
get artistic training
得到文藝的訓練
Next he said when I was young
下面他說我年輕的時候呢
Follow my father out to be an official
隨著我的父親出去做官
Then I have experienced many mountains and rivers
那麼我經歷了許多的民山大川
what about father
那麼父親呢
My parents love me very much
父母親對我非常非常的疼愛
Although in my literature and art
雖然呢我的文藝之中
There is no way to talk to this kind of rich girl who has not entered the era
沒有辦法跟這種未進時代的財女
For example, who is Everlasting Wealth?
例如說永續之財是誰
Xie Daoyun
謝道韻
I can't talk to Xie Daoyun
我沒有辦法跟謝道韻
Or another rich woman who wrote flowers to send
或者是寫交花送的另外一個財女
This Ms. Chen
這個陳女士
compared to
相比
but
但是呢
He said I can't compare
他說我不能比
In fact, I want to compare
其實就是想要比
Do you guys know this rhetoric?
各位知道這種修辭嗎
Fama
法馬
OK
OK
Although I am not as good as them
雖然我是比不上他們了
And what?
而且呢
The tube system in my pen is my pen
我的筆下管系就是我的筆下
Do I dare to write the eternal things in my pen?
我的筆下難道我敢去寫千古事嗎
do i dare to go
難道我敢去
Just like Li Qingzhao we mentioned earlier
像剛才我們說的李清照一樣
to reflect on history?
去反思歷史嗎
Oh I dare not
哎呀我不敢啊
I don't dare to say it, but I really want it
說不敢其實就是很想要
then what do i dare to do
那麼我只敢怎麼樣
Haoduan writes in solidarity
豪端細寫在聲援
then we see here
那我們看到這裡
he used a small word
他用了一個細字
This fine print is true on the one hand
這個細字呢一方面是真的
because he was a child
因為他還是個孩子
he is a teenager
他是個青少年
writing seemed to him
寫作對他來說好像是
yes it's a game
是是遊戲的
But on the other hand this fine
但另一方面這個細呢
Too
也是
It is a kind of original intention of creation
是一種創作的一個初心
without any power
是沒有任何功力之心的
i just want to write
我就是想要寫
i just want to create
我就是想要創作
I just wanna make up a story
我就是想要編造一個故事
Then Cheng Duansheng at this time is very lucky
那麼這個時候的承端生非常幸運囉
Because my loving mother saw what I wrote
因為我的慈母看到我寫的東西
Will smile lovingly to teach me
會露出慈愛的微笑來教導我
what should be done
應該要怎麼做才對
Then I eat children
那麼我這個吃兒女
My silly daughter is by my mother's side
我這個傻女兒就在母親的身邊
I told her my dreams
就跟她說的我的夢話
But since my mother died
但是自從母親過世以後
I am no longer in the mood to write
我就不再有心情寫了
I put down my pen
我就放下了我的才筆
Then I omitted a large part in the middle
那麼中間我省略了一大段
It's really very long
它這個真的寫得非常的長
and after
後來呢
I went back to my hometown with my family
我隨著全家回到故鄉歸照
It's the boat that goes back home
就是坐著回鄉的這個船
the boat goes very slowly
船走得非常的慢
So I have a lot of time to waste
所以我有大把大把的時間可以浪費
then what should we do
那怎麼辦呢
I will take out the manuscript of my novel
我就把我的這個小說的稿子拿出來
I wonder if I can write again
我想我是不是可以再寫啊
Born to be a leisurely man, if I have nothing to do, I will write again
生歸閒俠 沒事做我就再寫吧
At this time, in fact, I have misled some religious truths.
這個時候呢 其實呢 我已經誤導了一些宗教的道理
Which means I don't want to follow the right path in life.
也就是說 我不想要遵循人生的那個正道
What is the right way, what is the right way for women
正道是什麼 女性的正道是什麼
That is, you want to be a daughter, a father, and a mother, right?
就是你要為女 為父 為母 對不對
He said I don't want 'cause I misled some zen
他說 我不想要 因為我誤導了一些禪機
Then everyone should pay attention to the fact that in the Ming and Qing Dynasties, the pursuit of religion
那各位要注意 其實在明清時期 宗教的追求
also become a very very important one for women
也成為女性一個非常非常重要的一個
The so-called ultimate pursuit is to surpass oneself
所謂終極追求 也就是超越自己的
A way of gender limiting
性別限制的一種方式
Well, Chen Duansheng also said the same thing, it's a pity that Ke Nai is still in the vulgar world
那麼 陳端生也這麼說 可惜 可耐 餘歸俗類前
At this time, he has no way to break through absolutely
他在這個時候 並沒有辦法 絕絕的衝破
The so-called right way of life for women, this life plan added to him
所謂女性的人生正道 所加給他的這個人生規劃
So he's still married. After marriage, it's just like vulgarity.
所以他還是結婚了 結婚了以後呢 就俗類前了
here we see marriage is what we see here
在這裡我們看到 婚姻是我們所看到這裡
A Life of All the Women Writers
所有的女作家的一個人生的
turning point
轉折點
However, Chen Duansheng was very lucky at the beginning
不過呢 陳端勝一開始還是很幸運的
He said my Wengu was good to me
他說我的溫故對我很好
my husband is a confidant
我的丈夫是一個知心人
We light up and half read
我們挑燈半讀
On the one hand, he is in charge of checking, and on the other hand, I accompany him to study.
一面主查 一面我配著他讀書
Not only that, we also remind teachers
不但如此我們還科竹催師
Burn out the candle
以蠟燭燒完為渡
Let's compete who can do things faster
來比賽誰做事做得快
we can imagine how
我們可以想像這是多麼
A happy homely couple
愉快的一種歸中的夫婦之情
Of course, this should also remind us of
當然這個也應該讓我們聯想到
The relationship between Li Qingzhao and Zhao Mingcheng
李清照跟趙明成的關係
This is a so-called
這是一個所謂的
contemporary scholars call it
當代的學者稱之為
A relationship of partner marriage
夥伴婚姻的一種關係
That is to say, in the traditional marriage system,
也就是說在傳統的婚姻制度裡面
Originally between the couple
本來夫婦之間
Seems like there's only one kind of family obligation
似乎只有一種家庭的義務才對
But what about partner marriages?
但是呢 夥伴婚姻呢
But it can create a kind of mutual understanding between couples
卻可以營造一種夫婦彼此知心
not only have feelings
不但有感情
And this cultural exchange
還有這個文化的交流的
this way of marriage
這種婚姻方式
Therefore, Chengzhuan students in this period
所以這個時期的承專生
Not only a successful marriage
不但是婚姻順遂
And there are descendants
而且還有了後代
for him at this time
這個時候對他來說
It's really the end of life
真的是人生的順盡
It's a pity that his husband was forced by the so-called force
可惜他的丈夫卻受到了所謂的力所
Minjiang is asking Ke Ming
民疆 就是要求柯明
to pursue a career
為了想要追求某一種事業
and apparently committed a crime
而顯然是犯了案
It's the section chief's fraud case.
就是犯了科長的舞弊案
he can't say here
他在這裡是不能說的
because the first aspect is embarrassing
因為第一方面是很丟臉的事
The second aspect we just said
第二方面我們剛才說過
The section chief's case is a major case, Shatou's crime
科長案是大案 是沙頭的罪
Therefore, Chengzhuan is not obvious
所以承專生是不明顯的
then the end is
那麼結局就是
Here he uses two images
在這裡他用了兩個意象
One is to break the suspicion and the other is to break the ban
一個是斷嫌 一個是破禁
Of course both point to a broken marriage
當然這兩者都指向的是破碎的婚姻
symbol of an unhappy marriage
一個不幸的婚姻的象徵
Then under his husband is another
那麼他的丈夫下面又是一個
He didn't say it directly but we could read it
他沒有直說 但我們讀得出來
Group eyes open outside the setting sun
群 睁眼 斜陽外
His husband was exiled far away
他的丈夫被流放到了遠方
no longer with this family
不再跟這個家人在一起了
And it's one of the sidelines
而且是積屢在賽邊的一個
sad exile
愁苦的流放之人
What about Chen Duansheng?
那麼陳端生呢
Of course he's been sad ever since
他就從此當然就是傷心
This mark is messed up
這個 痕 混斷
He said that for many years
他就說 多年以來呢
He is in a state of extreme distress
他都是處在一種極度的憂苦當中
What about him, there is no way to reciprocate
他呢 沒有辦法回報
The relationship between his husband and him
他的丈夫跟他之間的感情
he can only watch
他只能夠看著
His two sons and daughters worked hard to survive
他的一雙兒女努力的活下去
then he said for him
那麼他說 對他來說
this home he lives in
他所處的這個家園
like a castle
就如同一座城堡一樣
lock him in
把他關在裡面
Let him be a hatred
讓他日做仇成
Although he wants to fly to her husband's side
雖然他想要飛到丈夫的身邊
But there's no African American, right?
但是身無雙非裔 對嗎
There is nothing he can do about Fengyan
他主於風煙是沒有辦法
reunited with his husband
再跟他的丈夫團圓
You see we read from this text
你看我們從這段文字裡面
We can probably see that Chen Duansheng narrated
我們大概就可以看到陳端生他敘述了
he grew up
他從小長大
This literary training in the rules
在規中的這個文藝的訓練
The practice of literature and art between parents and sisters
跟父母跟姊妹之間的這個文藝的實踐
life after marriage
婚姻之後的生活的方式
his relationship with his husband
他跟他丈夫的關係
misfortune suffered by his husband
他丈夫所招受到的不幸
and his own fate
以及他本人的命運
Is it all written in this paragraph?
是不是都在這一段話裡面寫出來了
So this master of the twentieth century, Mr. Chen Yingque
所以這個二十世紀的這個大師陳英雀先生
He will be able to follow the clues here
他就能夠根據這裡面的線索
To compare some other historical records of the Qing Dynasty
去對照清代的一些其他的歷史記錄
to compare
去比對
And finally came to this conclusion
而最後得出這個結論
is the author of Regenerated Source
就是再生源的作者
It's Chen Duansheng
就是陳端生
Then such a form of creation
那麼這樣子的一種的形式的創作
We can see that
我們可以看到
this is the author
就是這個作者
He is writing a novel on the one hand
他一方面是在寫一部小說
But on the one hand he is writing about himself
但一方面他是在寫自己
He couldn't help but write himself in
他忍不住要把自己寫進去
Because he was really afraid of writing it himself
因為他真的怕自己寫進去
Just this area of ​​flesh and blood is invincible with the disappearance of his life
就這血肉之區就隨著他的生命的消失而什麼都不勝
I think it's a very, very deep kind of fear
我覺得這是一種非常非常深沉的一種恐懼
because of this fear
因為有這種恐懼
So these women have an urge to create
所以這些女性她就有一個創作的衝動
We just said that the previous part of this regeneration source
我們剛才說過這個再生源的前面的一部分
That is to say, the first sixteen volumes were written by this Chen Duansheng when he was a young girl
也就是前十六卷是這個陳端生在少女的時候寫成的
The order of this section of the seventeenth volume has a
這第十七卷的這一段的秩序就有一個
Looking at the role of experience in the first half of your life
縱觀自己前半生的經歷的作用
The cultivation of this talented woman she described here
她在這裡面所敘述的這個才女的養成
and their married life
以及他們的婚後的生活
In fact, among the talented women of Ming and Qing Dynasties, they are quite representative.
其實在明清才女當中是具有相當的代表性的
We can also see Chen Duansheng here
我們在這裡也可以看到陳端生
His entire narrative voice changed
他整個的敘述的聲音改變了
Because you only see this part, so you can't feel it
因為各位只看到這一段所以你沒辦法感受
If we read from the first volume
如果我們是從第一卷就開始看的話
we will clearly see
我們會非常明顯的看到
Chen Duansheng the author
陳端生這個作者
when he was the narrator
他作為敘事者的時候
His tone changed completely
他的語氣完全的改變了
from a clueless
從一個不知事事
very happy to write
非常愉快寫作
just for the game
只是為了遊戲
Just to make mom happy like this one
只是為了讓媽媽高興這樣的一個
innocent girl
天真的少女
transformed into a person who experienced Tibet
轉變到了一個歷經人士藏藏
And one who is very dissatisfied with society
而且對於社會非常不滿的一個
middle-aged woman
中年婦女
An image of a woman who has experienced Tibet
一個歷經藏藏的一個婦女的一個形象
So
那麼
He can no longer use a kind of tenderness
他再也沒有辦法以一種溫柔燈後
or the attitude of the game
或者是遊戲的態度
To face this fate of women
來面對女性的這個命運
good
好
Then we can see here
那麼我們在這裡就可以看到
What about Tan Ci's novels?
譚慈小說呢
he has a lot of space in him
他裡面有很多的空間
What about the women of the Ming and Qing Dynasties?
讓這個明清的 清代的女性呢
can express one's true self
可以表達真正的自我
Next, let's take a look at the development centered on this Regeneron.
接下來我們來看一看以這個再生元為中心發展出來的
A whole series of romance novels about love for women
一整個系列的情代女性談慈小說
Regeneron, we are the first to talk about it is definitely not without reason
再生元我們第一個講絕對不是沒有原因的
because it is a true classic of women's love fiction
因為它是女性談慈小說的真正的經典之作
Not only is the work itself complete, but the plot and characters are designed
不但這個作品本身這個結構完整情節人物設計的
are very attractive
都非常有魅力之外
It also has topics that many women will find interesting
它還有一些議題是許多女性都會感到有興趣的
So centered on Regeneron we can see that there is a network of text
所以以再生元為中心我們可以看到有一個文本的網絡
a web with a text
有一個文本的一張網
In this web we can see female narrative literature
在這張網裡面我們可以看到女性敘事文學
A Development Track of Women's Novels
女性小說的一個發展的軌跡
There are several key points in this track
在這個軌跡裡面有幾個重點
what are the key points
哪些重點呢
First, women are going out into the public domain
第一 女性要走出门 进入公领域
The second is to establish a personal public enterprise, a personal industry
第二 要建立个人的公众事业 个人的工业
The third is to explore the multiple possibilities of women's feelings and even friendship
第三 要探索女性的感情 甚至情谊的多重的可能性
Fourth, we must pursue the ultimate meaning of human life
第四 要追求人类的终极的生命意义
These key points will be included in these many works
这几个重点会在这许多的作品里面
constantly being repeated and performed
不断地被重复而且演绎着
Of course, these are works of the Qing Dynasty
当然了 这些都是清朝的作品
So it has the limitations of its age
所以它有它时代的限制
So we said just now that there is a prerequisite for going out and establishing a public company
所以我们刚才说 走出门 建立公业都有一个前提
It's just that it doesn't do these things as a woman
就是它不会以女性的身份去做这些事情
It has to be like what we just saw
它一定都要像我们刚才看到的
Meng Lijun from the small country village, right?
那个国小庄业的孟丽君 对不对
it must be dressed as a male
它一定要扮成一个男性
with a masculine mask after wearing a masculine mask
用一个男性的 戴上了男性的面具之后
He was able to get out of the boudoir, he was able to build an industry
他才能夠走出閨門 他才能夠建立工業
He is able to pursue lust and so on
他才能夠去追求情慾等等
These are a necessary design
這些是一個必要的設計
So what you see on the screen
所以各位在螢幕上面所看到的
Almost all works involve a key to the plot
幾乎所有的作品都牽涉著一個情節的關鍵
it's called crossdressing
就叫做女伴男裝
and as we have just said
還有我們剛才已經說過
The Female Writers of the Ming and Qing Dynasties
這個明清時代的女作家
There is a big difference between them and the female writers of the Song Dynasty
他們跟宋代的女作家有一個很大的差別
That is, women in the Ming and Qing Dynasties would actively pursue a sense of community
就是明清的女性會主動的去追求一個社群感
No matter the community is our whole family girls can write
不管這個社群是我們全家的女生都會寫作
Or the female literary talents in our Huxiang area are very powerful
或者是我們這個湖鄉地區的女性文藝之才都很厲害
Or our talented women in Hangzhou are very powerful, etc.
或者是我們杭州的才女都很厲害等等
They will pursue a sense of community
他們會追求一種群體感
This is of course for our contemporary
這個當然對於我們當代
We are all so familiar with community culture in modern times
現代我們都這麼熟悉社群文化
For example, we are now live
例如我們現在在直播
Maybe everyone who is watching the live broadcast
可能所有在看直播的人
feel that they are in the same
都覺得自己是處在同一
In the same field even though we are far apart
同一個場域之中 即使我們其實相隔的很遠
So this feeling is actually
所以這種感覺其實在
Women in the Ming and Qing Dynasties were also pursuing
明清時期的女性 她們一樣在追求的
So how do they pursue
那麼她們怎麼追求呢
They certainly don't have modern technology
她們當然沒有現代的科技
But what, they can text
但是呢 她們可以透過文本
they will text
她們會經過文本
and responses to the text to create this sense of community
以及對文本的回應來營造這一種社群感
This is a literary community
這是一種文藝社群
Then the renewable source is such a kind
那麼再生源呢 就是這樣的一種
A center for an imaginative literary community
想像性的文藝社群的一個中心
Then we can probably see
那我們大概可以看到
In fact, the source of reproduction is not an isolated work.
其實再生源 它並不是一個孤立的作品
before it was
在它之前呢 就有
This may not be the head
這個可能還不是頭啊
This is the earliest header I can trace back so far
這是我目前能夠追溯到的最早的一個頭
Two works called Big Money and Little Money
是叫做大金錢與小金錢的兩部作品
Together they are called making money
它們合起來叫做金錢賺
We don't quite know when exactly it works
我們已經不太知道它究竟是什麼時候的作品
So is the author really a woman?
那麼作者是不是真的是女性
I'm not sure yet
我也還不敢完全的確認
but likely
不過很可能
Then after this there is a
那麼在這個之後呢 有一部
A work called "Jade String Garden"
叫做《玉串園》的作品
I'm pretty sure it's a woman's work.
这个作品我就非常确定是女性的创作了
Then in "Jade String Garden", there is also a talk about female companions and men's clothing
那么在《玉串園》里面也是有讲到女伴男装
Well, when Chen Duansheng wrote "Reborn Circle"
那么陈端生他在写《再生圆》的时候
He started by saying
他一开头就说
I read a book called "Jade String Garden"
我读了一部书叫做《玉串園》
very nice
很好看
But I'm very dissatisfied with his ending
可是我非常不满意他的结局
There's a woman in it that I think is pretty good
里面有一个我认为非常优秀的女性
Didn't get a very fair treatment in the ending
在结局里面竟然没有得到非常公平的待遇
I think there's a sense of injustice in this
我认为这个有一股不平之气
so i'm writing a new novel
所以我要创作一本新的小说
To reverse the case of a female character I identify with
来替我认同的女性人物翻案平反
This is his motivation for writing "The Reborn Circle" in the first place.
这个就是他一开始写《再生圆》的动机
Because of this, his novel is called "Reborn Circle"
正因为如此 所以他的小说叫做《再生圆》
right
对不对
Because his heroine Meng Lijun
因为他的女主角孟立军
In fact, she said it was a secondary character in "Jade String Circle"
其实她说是《玉串圆》里面的一个次要角色的
what is it called
这叫什么样
afterlife afterlife
後生 後世 再世
I can't remember what it's called in Chinese
我一直想不起來那個中文叫什麼
that is
就是
afterlife
來生
OK good next life
OK 好 來生
good
好
Then he is using such a form
那麼他就是利用這樣的一個形式
to create his Regeneron
來創作他的這個再生元
Okay, so we can say that Regeneron is
好 那麼我們可以說再生元就是
A sequel to Yu Chuanyuan
御傳元的一個續集了
But he's not a sequel
可是呢他又不是一個續集
he's a whole new story
他是一個全新的故事
So on the one hand
那麼一方面呢
He did inherit the elements in Yu Chuanyuan.
他的確繼承了這個御傳元裡面的
some characters
若干的人物
but
但是呢
He's not like Yu Chuanyuan
他不像御傳元
on the basic spirit
在基本的精神上面
Unlike Midenmoto
不像御傳元
Because of Yu Chuanyuan
因為御傳元呢
What about the woman he wrote about in disguise?
他寫的這個女伴男裝呢
is a comparison
是比較
Um
嗯
Well
呃
It's just for plot advancement
只是為了情節推進而用的
It's just for this man and woman to get together
只是為了讓這個男女相聚而用的
He's not really trying to explore women's potential
他不是真正要探索女性的潛能
or possibility
或者是可能性
This Meng Lijun written by Chen Duansheng
這個陳端生所寫的孟立軍
He wholeheartedly wants to be here
他就一心一意的要在這個
The image of Meng Lijun he created has made a big fuss
他所塑造的孟立軍的這個形象上面去大作文章
He wants to explore through Meng Lijun
他要通過孟立軍來探索
The various possibilities of this woman's life
這個女性生命的各種的可能性
then we must also say
那麼我們也必須說
In this earlier novel
在這個比較早的這個小說裡面呢
If the hero and heroine can get married and have a happy reunion
男女主角如果能夠成婚大團圓
that's perfect
那就是完美的
don't say anything else
不用再說別的了
that's a perfect ending
那就是一個完美的結局
But for Chen Duansheng
可是對於陳端生來說
that's not the end
那不是終點
So we see that there are
所以我們看到在再生議員裡面有
very very long episode
非常非常長的情節
It's describing Meng Lijun's repulsion
是在描寫孟立軍如何的排斥
push the final destination
推劇那個最後的終點
he keeps
他不斷的
If Meng Lijun admits that marriage is his final destination
如果他孟立軍承認婚姻是他最後的終點的話
In fact, he is constantly working hard to delay the arrival of this end point.
他其實是不斷的努力的在推遲這個終點的到來
This is the most important part of the regeneration councilor
這個是再生議員最重要的一部分
At the same time we must also note
同時我們也必須注意到
in this novel
在這個小說裡面
his maiden
他的未婚
Instruct Huangfu Shaohua, we just said that he is a student of Meng Lijun
吩咐黃府少華我們剛才說過是孟立軍的學生
Therefore, we must put on a very aggressive attitude in front of Meng Lijun
所以必須在孟立軍的面前擺出非常趨入的姿態
but no matter
但無論如何
In the novel, Huangfu Shaohua is a man who refuses to marry because of Meng Lijun
黃府少華在小說裡面是為了孟立軍而不肯結婚的男人
Don't we sound moved?
我們聽起來是不是滿感動的
If it was a female reader at the time, she would say
如果是當時的女性讀者看了一看就說
I'm so touched. There is absolutely no such man in this world.
太感動了這世界上絕對不可能有這樣的男人
should think so
應該是這樣想
But if we look at it with the eyes of modern people
但是如果我們以現代人的眼光來看的話
Huangfu Shaohua in this novel has been in his first service for three years
這小說裡面的黃府少華他首役三年
It is not confirmed that Meng Lijun is dead, he refuses to get married
沒有確定孟立軍死掉他不肯結婚
Is it just for mood?
只是為了意氣嗎
just for love
只是為了愛情嗎
maybe more than that
可能不止對不對
especially when he saw that his teacher
尤其是當他看出了他的老師
That is, the prime minister
也就是當朝的宰相
Possibly his fiancée
很可能就是他的未婚妻
And when he was trying to bring Meng Lijun back to his family
而他努力的要把孟立軍帶回他的家庭的時候
In fact, his real pursuit is not just love.
其實他真正的追求不只是愛情
It is the restoration of a restored family
更是一個復全家庭的恢復
right
對不對
It is a recovery system
這是一個復全制度的
Consolidation again
再次的鞏固
masculinity again
再做的男性氣
Don't blame me for being so negative about rehab
不要埋怨我如此負面的戒毒
The character Huang Fu Shaohua
黃府少華這個人物
well then
好 那麼
OK, so we see this cross-dressing design
OK 那我們看到這個女扮男裝的設計
In this garden of regeneration and her previous works
在這個 再生園以及她之前的作品裡面
has undergone some changes
已經就經歷了一些變化了
And in the later works of this series
而在後面的這個系列的作品裡面
She's still going to have a lot of renditions
她仍舊會發生許許多多的演繹
But her effect will be different
不過她的效果是會不一樣的
I'm very rough here
我在這裡很粗略的把
Some of the works I have experienced are divided into two series
我所經驗的一些作品分成兩個系列
The series on the left is
左邊的這個系列是
It can be said to be the sequel to Garden of Regeneration
可以說是再生園的續集
That is to say
也就是說
The female authors of the series on the left
左邊這個系列的女性作者們
They all publicly said that I watched Garden of Regeneration
他們都公開的說我是因為看了再生園
i am moved or i am dissatisfied
我感動或者是我不滿
That's why I wrote a new work
所以我才寫一個新的作品
to respond to him
來回應他
So the works on the left are all directly responding to the regeneration source
所以左邊這些作品都是直接在回應再生源的
And the series on the right
而右邊的這一系列作品
They appeared a little later
他們出現的年代稍微晚一些
Probably until the middle or late 19th century
大概都要到19世紀的中葉或19世紀末
they didn't say directly
他們就並沒有直接說
I'm because I watched the regeneration source
我是因為看了再生源
That's why I came to write my novel
所以才來寫我的小說
But the traces of the middle influence
但是中間的影響的痕跡
It's actually very obvious
其實是非常明顯的
if we look at it in the future
我們以後見之明來看的話
Then through the investigation of these two series of works
那麼通過對於這兩個系列的作品的考察
If we focus on the issue of cross-dressing,
如果我們集中在女扮男裝這個議題上面的話
We can really see the different times
我們真的可以看到不同時代的
and female authors who think differently
以及不同的思維的女性作者
for the same problem
對於同樣的問題
What different ideas would they come up with
他們會提出什麼樣不一樣的想法
or the solution
或者說解決的辦法
Well, I'm actually in a hurry
那麼其實我的時間很趕
I try to be as fast as possible
我盡量快一點
Let's take a look at the one on the left
我們先來看看左邊那個
first part of the series
系列名的第一部
This one is about a female writer called "Liang Deshen"
這一部是一個叫做《梁德神》的女作家
Didn't we just say this
我們剛不是說這個
"Chen Duansheng" has not finished writing "Rebirth"
《陳端生》還沒有寫完《再生緣》
just passed away?
就不幸過世了嗎
Then everyone feels a pity
那麼大家都覺得好可惜
Because at that time, "Rebirth" was a
因為其實在當時《再生緣》是一個
Works that are very popular with readers
非常受到讀者喜愛的作品
no ending
沒有結局
This is like the drama you watched
這個就如同你看的一齊劇
It turned out that the last episode was locked.
結果竟然這個最後一集被鎖掉了
This feeling
這種感覺
Okay, so everyone feels so sorry.
好 所以大家都覺得太遺憾了
So there was a Ms. Liang Deshen
於是就有一位梁德神女士
She was actually a
她其實在當時是一個
An older one of the female literary world
女性文藝圈的一個比較年長的一個
leader
首領這樣一個身份的人
Then because she is older
那麼她因為比較年長
So her attitude is of course relatively peaceful.
所以她的態度當然就是比較平和的
She will not be like "Chen Duansheng"
她不會像《陳端生》那樣
after all the suffering of life
在受盡了人生的苦之後
There is a sense of grief and indignation
就有一股悲憤之氣
So what Liang Deshen has to do
那麼梁德神她要做的
is to flush this out
是把這個衝出
Works full of women's grievances
都滿了女性的不平之氣的作品
give her a softer ending
給她一個比較和緩的結局
so in general
所以一般來說
modern reader
現代的讀者
readers not necessarily
讀者還不一定
modern critics are very dissatisfied
現代的批評家都非常不滿意
The last ending written by Liang Deshen
梁德神所寫的最後面的結局
they all feel
他們都覺得
Doesn't this put this regenerated MP
這不就把這個再生議員
Is this story written too often?
這個故事給寫得頻繁掉了嗎
So if we look at it from a modern perspective
那麼我們以現代的眼光來看的話
indeed
確實如此
But Liang Deshen, with one
不過梁德神他以一個
Compare older women to women to write the story
比較年紀大的婦女女性來寫這個故事
He's not without what he's read
他也不是沒有他的讀到之處
For example, we just saw the show and knew
例如我們剛剛看表演就知道
This proverb is very suitable for describing delicate feelings
這個譚詞是非常適合用來描寫細緻的感情的
and inner reading
還有內心的讀白
Then actually read the truth
那麼其實內心讀白
It is relatively rare in traditional Chinese novels
是在傳統中國小說裡面比較少的
Except Hong Luomeng
除了紅羅夢
we rarely see
我們幾乎很少可以看到
A large section of inner psychological changes
大段的內心的心理的變化
but Tan Ci novels
但是譚詞小說
Because of the psychology of this Tanci performance
因為這個譚詞表演的心理
gave the writer this convenience
就給了作家這個便利
Let's say we see here
比方說我們在這裡看到
In this passage he wrote
這一段他寫的是
Meng Lijun and his fiancé Huangfu Shaohua
孟立軍跟他的未婚夫黃府少華
What about after the team member?
團員了之後呢
know this classic novel
知道這個古典小說嗎
In fact, that has all kinds of things
其實那個都有三七四切
So there is another
所以還有另外一個
a little lady
一個小夫人
This little lady was already in
這個小夫人呢其實本來已經在
Huangfu Shaohua is here
黃府少華身邊了
But Huangfu Shaohua refused to marry him
可是黃府少華就不肯跟他結婚
Said that I must find Meng Lijun
說我一定要找到孟立軍
So he was already fed up, right?
所以他以前就已經很吃憋了對不對
Seeing this Huangfu Shaohua and Meng Lijun
眼看這個黃府少華呢跟孟立軍
get married
結婚了
He was alone on the wedding night
結婚夜他一個人呢
Sitting alone in his home
獨坐在他的歸房裡面
what does he think
他怎麼想呢
he faces
他對著
to the candlelight
對著燭火
silent
默默無語
Must be a woman of the world
必須是一個世大體的女人
So I can't make noise, right?
所以我又不能夠去吵鬧對不對
I can't go to barbarian
我又不能去蠻院
But I'm really worried
可是我真的好擔心喔
This Meng Lijun used to be prime minister
這個孟立軍他曾經當過宰相
and he is so fierce
而且他那麼兇
what would he do to me like that
他那樣對我怎麼辦
And what about this Huangfu Shaohua?
而且呢這個黃府少華呢
I used to be so good to him but he refused to marry me
以前我對他那麼好 他卻不肯跟我結婚
Is he affectionate or heartless?
他到底是有情還是無情呢
If this Meng Lijun is an idle person, I'll forget it
如果這個孟立軍他是一個閒晦的人我也就算了
What the hell would I do if he wasn't a slob
如果他不是一個閒晦的人我到底怎麼辦
I'm helpless
我無依無靠
Because his father is a treacherous minister, he has been arrested by this
因為他的父親是一個奸臣已經被這個
has been wrecked
已經失事了
ok then we can see
好 那麼我們可以看到
Through this Ms. Liu's inner monologue
透過這個劉女士他的這個內心獨白
In fact, Liang Desheng showed us
其實梁德省他給我們看到了
a traditional polygamy
一個傳統多妻
polygamous family
不能說多妻家庭
A woman in a family with wives and concubines
就是有妻妾的家庭裡面的女性
A complexity in his heart
他的心裡面的一個複雜度
He is not like the kind of wives and concubines written in this series
他並沒有像這個連續劇裡面寫的那種妻妾活拼
What are you going to do with poison?
什麼要下毒藥啊什麼的
Or throw some other party's child to death?
或是要把什麼對方的孩子丟死啊
take the dog to bite him
拿狗去咬他
no he didn't write like this
沒有 他不是寫這樣
He will tell you how ungrateful and fierce this heart is.
他就告訴你這個心裡面有多麼的頗逃兇容
This is enough
這就夠了
good
好
This is a detailed description of female psychology by a female writer
這是一個女作家對於女性心理的一種細緻的描寫
look at the next example
你看下一個例子
This is another female writer named Hou Zhi
這個是另外一個女作家叫做侯芝
She is also a woman who has the position of leader in the female literary circle
她同樣的是一個具有女性文藝圈當中首領位置的女性
Her husband is soft round student
她的丈夫是軟圓的學生
This Hou Zhi is very, very interesting
這個侯芝就非常非常有趣
she's a super complicated woman
她真是一個超級複雜的女性
On the one hand, she has to put on a
一方面她又要擺出一副
She is a female teacher gesture
她是一個女性的老師的姿態
So she wants to teach women to obey the rules
所以她要教導女性文大家都要守規矩
You know what? If you don't follow the rules
你知道嗎?如果不守規矩的話
there will be riots
是會鬧亂子的
but on the other hand
可是另外一方面
she's done some really weird things herself
她自己就做過一些非常奇怪的事
For example, she obviously belongs to a famous family
比方說她明明是一個名門的歸宿
But she was able to contact the publisher
但是她竟然可以去聯絡出版商
Help Her Publish Commercial Publishing
幫她出版商業出版
help her publish her novel
幫她出版她的小說
Did you know that Chen Dunshen did such a thing?
你知道陳敦深做過這種事嗎?
absolutely not
絕對不會的
so we can see
所以我們可以看到
A traditional woman, he has many complex layers
一個傳統女性,他有很多複雜的層面
We really can't learn from what he said
我們其實真的不能夠從他所說的話
or what he wrote to judge him
或他所寫的文字去判斷他
You have to put him together on all levels
你必須從各種層面把他匯集在一起看
He will be a three-dimensional person
他才會是一個立體的人
Well, this Hou Zhi has actually rewritten Fate of Rebirth
那麼這個侯知他其實也改寫過再生緣
What about after he rewrote it?
那麼他改寫過了以後呢
he rewrites , so he has to read , right
他改寫嘛,所以他要讀,對不對
What about women, they are the best readers for women
那麼女性呢,就是女性最好的讀者
As for Hou Zhi, he read it completely
這個侯知呢,他就完全的讀到了
The Charm of Chen Duansheng's Fate of Rebirth
陳端生的再生緣的魅力
But he also read about his danger
但是他同樣的也讀到了他的危險性
Because after seeing the fate of rebirth, it will be in the hearts of women
因為看了再生緣是會在女性的心中
planted a seed of uneasiness
種下一個不安的種子的
Then as a life coach
那麼作為一個人生導師
Hou Zhi like this, he thinks he can't do things like this
這樣的侯知呢,他覺得他不能夠做事這種情況
So, he wrote another novel
所以呢,他又寫了一部小說
The novel is called Reinvention
這部小說叫做再造天
That is to say
也就是說
Simply put, the story of Rebirth
簡單的說,再生緣這個故事
with his subsequent role
以他的後續的作用
It's like breaking the sky
就好像把天給打破了似的
Break the harmony of the world, yin and yang, men and women
把這個天地的 陰陽的 男女的這個和諧給打破了
I have to make it up again
我必須要再把它補起來
So he wrote this book called "The Novel of Reinventing the Sky"
所以他寫了這個叫做《再造天的小說》
It says
裡面是說
This Meng Lijun married Huangfu Shaohua and gave birth to a daughter
這個孟栗君跟黃浦少華結婚以後生了一個女兒
Just as smart and beautiful as him
就跟他一樣的聰慧美麗
only
只不過
Because I was spoiled by Mr. Meng Li
因為被孟栗君寵壞了
So her temper and her ambition are more out of the ordinary than Meng Lijun
所以她的脾氣以及她的志向比孟栗君更出格
This daughter said since she was a child
這個女兒從小就說
i want to be a dancer day
我要當舞者天
if
如果
when we are now affected by zero sequels
當了我們現在受到零續劇的影響
So if your daughter says she wants to be a dancer
所以如果你的女兒說要當舞者天
you may be happy
你可能心喜有佳
but
但是呢
I know
我知道
To be a dancer in this novel
在這個小說裡面要當舞者天
this is a very serious matter
這是一件非常嚴重的事情
really
果然
This daughter will really become a queen
這個女兒她就真的當上了皇后
After becoming queen
當上了皇后以後
She is really heading towards becoming a dancer step by step
她就真的一步一步朝向當舞者天的
go to this goal
這個目標前去
Of course, this country is in turmoil and the world is in chaos.
那當然就這個國家動盪天下大亂
In the end, the warehouse that caused this piece of land needs to be cleaned up.
最後造成了這個片地的倉儀需要收拾
what about this time
那麼這個時候呢
This mother, Meng Lijun, appeared
這個母親孟立軍他就出現了
Because the focus is not on Meng Lijun's daughter
因為重點其實並不在孟立軍的女兒
What kind of earth-shaking things did you do?
到底做了怎樣的天翻地覆的事
The focus is on the character Meng Lijun
重點在於孟立軍這個人物
how to reflect on your past
怎麼樣反省自己的過去
Let's see, this is another inner monologue
那我們看看這又是一段內心獨白
what about here
那麼在這裡面呢
This Meng Lijun
這個孟立軍
His daughter has been in this terrible disaster
他的女兒已經闖下了這個滔天大禍了
Meng Lijun says
孟立軍說
Back then, I just wanted to be an official
當年的我就為了當官
my mother is sick
我的母親生病了
dying
病重將死
I couldn't bear to see her
我竟然忍心不去看她
my husband fiance
我的丈夫未婚夫
because miss me miss me lovesickness
因為思念我想念我相思病
dying too
也是快要死了
I am not only not moved
我不但不感動
He hates me and I think he loves the world
他讨厌 我还嫌他爱世
Then I just think about my husband insisting on me being with him
那么我只想到我的丈夫硬要我跟他
where is my fiancé
我的这个未婚夫呢
my student my student insisted that i marry him
我的弟子 我的学生硬要我跟他结婚
is a disgraceful thing
是一件恥辱的事情
I'm a teacher, how can I marry my student?
我是老师 怎么可以嫁给我的学生呢
Then I completely ruined this family of mine.
那么我完全就是害了我的这个家人
he he is my daughter
他 他就是我的女儿
My daughter wants to learn from Wu Zetian to steal the country
我的女儿呢 要学武则天去窃国
what about me
我又怎么样呢
Back then, I was just practicing for the position of prime minister.
我当年呢 只不过练着宰相之位呢
I'm right, uh, to the emperor, to my father, to my husband
我就对 呃 对皇帝 对父亲 对丈夫呢
so disrespectful
都如此的不敬
think about it now
现在想起来
Everything that's happening now is retribution
所有现在发生的一切都是报应
It's all because of my bad behavior in the past
都是因为我以前行为有差
So I'm suffering now, uh, totally deserved
所以我现在受这些折磨 呃 完全是应该的
Wasn't what I did before just like Qingshou?
我以前做的是不就跟情寿一样吗
No wonder what my daughter is doing now is more vicious than tigers and wolves
怪不得我的女儿现在做的是比虎狼还要凶狠
good
好
Although I am talented
我虽然有才
I though
我虽然呢
Conspiracy
有寄謀
Although I never thought of harming anyone before
我雖然以前從來沒有想過要害人
but
但是呢
as a female
作為一個女性
What I absolutely shouldn't be is that I'm greedy to blend in
我萬萬不該的是我去貪戀融入
I shouldn't just think about being an officer
我不應該只想著要做官
have to wait
要等等
Then I won't talk about it
那麼下面我就不講了
I mean, my daughter is like this now.
意思就講說現在我女兒已經這樣了
I must strictly discipline my granddaughter
我以後一定要對我的孫女嚴家管教
must make her a
一定要讓她變成一個
Well-Being Women
財德俱全的女性
Well, this is Hou Zhijie
好這個是侯知介者
Meng Lijun's
這個孟立軍的
Meng Lijun reflects on his own words
孟立軍反省自己的話
to deliver a message to his readers
來傳達給他的讀者一個訊息
right
對不對
no matter how talented you are
就是不管你多麼有才
but you can't
但是你不可以
Obsessed with some so-called civic principles
執著於某一些所謂的公民理路
Of course here we have to say
當然在這裡我們必須說
Wait a minute
Wait a minute
This Ms. Hou, you completely misunderstood our Chen Duansheng
這個侯女士你完全了誤會我們陳端生
Meng Lijun written by Chen Duansheng
陳端生寫的孟立軍
Is he just greedy to fit in?
他只是貪戀融入嗎
no
不是啊
He is pursuing a life pursuit
他是在做一個人生的追求
why don't you see that side
你怎麼不看到那一面呢
because of this
因為如此
So contemporary readers and critics
所以當代的讀者以及批評家
Regarding what Hou Zhi wrote in
對於侯知所寫的在
In Zhaotian, of course, I don't particularly like it.
在照天當然也是不會特別喜歡
but even so
但即使如此
i still have to say
我還是必須說
if we revisit this
如果我們重新去看這個
"Hou Zhi" wrote that when the sky was shining
《侯知》所寫的在照天的時候
we can see
我們人就可以看到
When Hou Zhi imagines someone who wants to do
當侯知去想像一個想要做
The time of women in "Five Folds"
《五折天》的女性的時候
His writing actually reveals unconsciously
他的筆下其實不自覺的流露出
a mood
一種心情
a pleasure
一種痛快
So as for the last
那麼至於到最後這個
Meng Lijun's self-reflection
孟立軍的自我反省
cannot dissolve the middle of this novel
並不能夠消解這個小說中間
all those for this woman
所有的那些對於這個女性
I want to do "50% off the sky"
想要做《五折天》來
the will to rule the world
一統天下的那種意志
not digested
並沒有被消解
Then this is Zai Zhaotian from "Hou Zhi"
那麼這個是《侯知》的在照天
We can see that it is a negative response
我們可以看到它是一個負面的反應
then look at this
那麼再看看這個
This is about the nineteenth century
這個是十九世紀大概
A woman in the late
中後期的一位女性
She also watched "Rebirth"
她同樣也是看了《再生緣》之後
was very moved
受到了非常大的感動
she likes it
她很喜歡
But he also has a point
但是呢 他也有一點意見
His opinion is not about the Meng Lijun created by Chen Duansheng.
他的意見倒不是說這個陳端生所創造的孟立軍呢
This wants to be an official so much
這個 這麼想當官
his opinion is not here
他的意見不在這裡
This, Qiu Xinru's opinion is
這個 邱欣儒他的意見是
This Meng Lijun is too unfilial
這個孟立軍也太不孝了吧
Because Meng Lijun refused to restore women's clothing
因為孟立軍呢 不肯恢復女裝
So his parents were very, very worried
所以讓他的父母親都非常非常的擔心受怕 收金
And still seriously ill
而且還重病
Well, Qiu Xinru thinks that everything else is easy to say
那麼這個邱欣儒認為 別的都好說
People can't let their parents worry so much
人不可以讓父母親這麼的憂心
So at this point, he can't accept it at all.
所以在這一點上面 他就完全沒辦法接受
So he thinks, this dream of Meng Lijun's life
所以他認為呢 這個孟立軍的人生的這個夢想呢
he appreciates it very much
他非常的欣賞
But he thinks Meng Lijun is an imperfect character
但是呢 他認為孟立軍是一個不夠完美的人物
So he wanted to create a character
所以他想要創造一個人物
It has the material of Meng Lijun
既有孟立軍的這個材質
Can reach the same height as Meng Lijun's industrial
又能夠達到跟孟立軍一樣高度的工業
at the same time
同時又是
is a perfect person
是一個人格完美的人
So guys, do you think this is possible?
那各位想想這有沒有可能呢
Everyone is so optimistic
大家都好樂觀
Y'all, I thought everyone was going to say no way right away.
你們都 我還以為大家都馬上都會說不可能
It's really hard
其實真的很難
So
那麼
This Qiu Xinru is here
這個邱欣儒他在這個
Bishenghua Bishenghua means this book is very good, right?
比生花 比生花意思是說這本書很好看對不對
Myohi Ikebana
妙比生花
he is here
他在這個
What about a character created in Bishenghua's novel?
比生花這個小說裡面所創造出來的一個人物呢
In all respects
在各方面
Whether it's character settings
不管是人物設定也好
As far as his life experiences are concerned
到他的人生遭遇也好
In fact, they are all very, very similar to Meng Lijun
其實都跟孟立軍非常非常的像
The only difference is
唯一的不同呢就是
What about the character he created?
他所創造的這個人物呢
He will not be like Meng Lijun
他不會像孟立軍一樣
use so firmly
用那麼堅決
And violently collide with the system
而且激烈的方式去跟體制衝撞
what about his female character
他的這個女性人物呢
is taking a
是採取著一種
On the one hand, work hard to make contributions
一方面努力地去建功立業
On the other hand
另外一方面呢
What about your words and deeds?
又對自己的言行呢
Trying to
努力地
an image that tries to constrain
盡力地去制約的一個形象
Let's take a look at a short
我們不妨看看看一小段
This is his heroine
這個是他的女主角
It's the same thing again, heartbroken
同樣的又來了 內心度敗
He said that this is also the pressure he faced to restore women's clothing
他說這個也是他面臨了必須要恢復女裝的壓力
His parents and so on told him that
他的父母親等等都告訴他說
you can't go on like this
你不能再這樣下去了
Mom and Dad are in jail, need to hold grandchildren, etc.
爸爸媽媽牢啦 需要抱孫子等等
he's under a lot of pressure
他又很大的壓力
So he said it doesn't work
所以呢他說看來不行了
had to forget
只好算了
I have to make a copy
我必須要復本還原了
I have to go back to being a woman
我必須要恢復女性的身份了
Looks like I have to get married, right?
看來我必須要去結婚了對不對
blow off cross seam
吹消跨縫
This was supposed to be a perfect marriage
這本來應該是一個完美的婚姻的
A symbol of a happy marriage
美滿婚姻的一個象徵
If you congratulate someone on their marriage today
如果你今天祝賀人家結婚
It should be good that you write blow off the cross seam
你寫吹消跨縫應該是不錯的
but
但是呢
But he said blow off the cross seam thing
他卻說吹消跨縫這件事情
makes me very depressed
讓我非常的愁悶
Next he said
下面他就說了
If women in this world get married
這世界上的女性如果結婚了之後
there are so many unfree places
就有這麼多的不自由的地方
This is of course compared to his time in the past
這當然是對比他過去的這段時間
It's this male freedom I've ever enjoyed
是我曾經享受過的這個男性的自由
He said that even if someone exposed
他說 其實就算是人家揭發了
i am female
我是女性的身份
Even if things leak
就算是事情洩漏了
Then I have to take off my male officer
那麼我必須要拿掉我的男性的官
And the records of women in the book
而書上女性的記
Even so
就算是這樣
I'm fine, I don't want to get married
我也沒關係 我不要結婚
as long as you don't get married
只要不結婚就好
because as long as you don't get married
因為只要不結婚
I won't have those detentions.
我就不會有那些的拘遷不自由了
Although my heart is so
雖然我的心意是如此
But my mom and dad won't let me do that
但是我的爸爸 媽媽不會讓我這樣做的
They don't think it's a good life
他們認為這個不是好的人生
So when my parents ask me
那麼當父母親要求我的時候
I can't help it, I have to listen to them
我就沒辦法 我必須要聽從他們
Because if I don't listen to my parents
因為如果我不聽從父母親的意思的話
that would be so disrespectful
那就太不孝了
so so i thought
那麼所以我左思右想
I know my ambition in this life
我知道我今生的志向
I'm afraid there is no way to really achieve it.
恐怕就沒有辦法真正的達成了
so we can see
所以我們可以看到
this
這個
The woman in Bishenghua
比生花裡面的這個女性
The biggest difference between her and Meng Qianjun is that
她跟孟茜君最大的不同就是
She will pass through one of her own
她會透過一個自己的
What happens after the rational one becomes difficult?
理性的一個變難之後呢
she will take orders from women
她會接受女性的命令
She will put her dissatisfaction, wish
她會把她的不滿、蠻願
Feelings of injustice are buried
不平的情緒都給埋藏起來
And with a mask
而用面具
put on a mask and come out
帶上面具來走出來
to face her future life
去面對她未來的人生
This is mentioned in Bishenghua
這個是比生花裡面提出來的
Another option
另外一種方案
Of course this solution for us
當然這個方案對我們來說
seems to be less than perfect
似乎是不夠完美的
In Bishenghua, in fact
在比生花裡面其實
She also kept describing the heroine over and over again.
她也不斷地一再地去描述這個女主角
she went to the end
她一直到最後呢
Until the end of this novel
一直到這個小說結束呢
She is a last resort
她都是以一個不得已的
such a mood to face
這樣的一個心情來面對
Let's look at a very extreme example
下面我們要看一個很極端的例子
This is a really nice example
這是一個非常精彩的例子
We just said that there are many female
我們剛才說有很多的女性的
are constantly responding in various ways.
都不斷的用各種方式去回應
Some of the proposed
這個再生源所提出來的一些
The Dilemma of Women's Lives
女性生命的困境
Then it is true that the later the nineteenth century
那麼確實越到十九世紀的後面
There will be more and more strange answers
會出現越多奇怪的答案
really weird answer
真的是奇怪的答案
They will experiment with different ways of unraveling
他們會實驗不同的解套的方式
then imagine
那麼會去想像
The consequences of various ways of unwinding
各種解套的方式的這個後果
So let's look at this example
那麼我們來看看這個例子
This work is called "Flower Dream"
這個作品叫做《流花夢》
it has many special places
它有很多的特別的地方
first it's not this
第一個它不是這個
Created by the women of Jiang Zhe's generation
江者一代的女性所創作的
The author is Li Guiyu
這個作者叫做黎貴育
He actually grew up in Shaanxi when he was a child
他其實小時候是在這個陝西那裡長大的
Then when he grows up
那麼後來他長大了以後
He went all the way from the west to the far south and got married in Fujian
他從西邊一路到了最南邊到了福建結婚
So he himself is saying that he has passed
所以他本人等於說是經過了
a long time
很長的一段
In the end it settled in Fujian
最後它就是在福建定居的
Liu Huameng was created when he was in Fujian
劉花夢就是他在福建的時候所創作的
How many pieces of Liu Huameng are there? How many times?
這個劉花夢有多少張呢 有多少回呢
There are 360 ​​times
有360回
How many words? About 5 million words
多少字呢 大概500萬字
This may be the longest Chinese novel we now know
這可能是我們現在知道的最長的一部中國小說
Do you think there is such a book
各位有沒有覺得有這樣的書
And our books none of our textbooks tell us
而我們的書 我們的課本都沒有告訴我們
is that right
這對嗎
Such a creation of 5 million words
這樣一個500萬字的一個創作
not an obscure work
並不是一個默默無聞的著作
In fact, according to records in the Fujian area
其實根據紀錄在福建地區
it's a very very famous
這是一個非常非常有名
and popular works
而且受歡迎的著作
how popular is it
受歡迎到什麼程度
same it has no way to publish
同樣的 它沒有辦法出版
Because it is too much, it cannot be engraved
因為它太多了 是不能拿去刻的
think about it
你想想看拿去刻
Gou Taiming may be needed to sponsor
可能就需要郭台銘來贊助
In that era, Guo Taiming came to sponsor
在那個時代的郭台銘來贊助
it's going to cost too much
就要花太多錢了
So no matter what to do, use super
所以都是怎麼辦 都是用超的
Spread in the form of Gaoben
高本的形式流傳
How popular can it be?
可以受歡迎到什麼程度呢
In fact, there were bookstores in ancient times.
其實古時候就有租書店的
Rent a bookshop in the nineteenth century
在十九世紀的租書店
"Flower Dream" is one
《流花夢》就是一個
at least hateful works
至少可惡的作品
That is, everyone wants to rush
就是大家要搶著
works to rent
去租來看的作品
besides
還有
Another effect is
還有另外一個作用就是
it can be turned into a property
它可以變成一個財產
what kind of property
什麼樣的財產
it is
它是
part of dowry
嫁妝的一部分
That is to say
也就是說
when a girl was young
一個女孩子在年少的時候
she copied it herself
她就自己抄
or at home
或者是家裡的
Sisters and mothers help to copy
姐妹媽媽幫著抄
let her get married
讓她在結婚的時候
You can bring "Liuhuameng"
可以帶著《流花夢》
extra
帶到附加曲
become her own
變成她自己的
part of the property
財產的一部分
and may be transmissible
而且可能是可以流傳的
We record from such
我們從這樣的記錄
you can see
就可以看到
This is a
這是一個
how to get attention
怎麼樣受到重視
and favorite works
以及喜愛的作品
Interestingly
有趣的是
In fact, the author did not
這個作者其實他也沒有
finish this work
把這個作品寫完
He probably wrote up to 357.
他大概是寫到三百五十七吧
He wrote three hundred fifty-seven
他寫到三百五十七
die before writing
沒寫完就死掉了
later in the twentieth century
後來是到二十世紀
Only two modern female writers helped her finish writing
才有現代的兩個女作家幫她寫完
But because it was written to 357, the overall situation is actually determined
不過因為寫到357其實大局的底定
So she is not the same as Regeneron
所以她跟再生源不一樣
Chen Duansheng of Zaiyuan wrote a key point and stopped
再生源的陳端生寫到一個關鍵地方就停了
And Liu Huameng didn't stop until the end.
而劉花夢則是到了最後才停
In fact, the latter can be completed with a little bit of hard work.
後面其實只是稍微加油天促就可以完成了
The big picture of the novel has not been changed
這個小說的大局是沒有被改變的
This novel has 5 million words
這個小說竟然有500萬字
Of course I can't tell you what she's talking about.
我當然不可能跟各位講她到底在講什麼
too complicated
太複雜
She is involved in the stories of at least three generations of several big families
她牽涉到好幾個大家族至少三代的故事
So it should be called Family Saga
所以應該是叫做Family Saga
This is the Yamato novel
就是這種大和小說
There is no way to effectively introduce to you
是沒有辦法跟各位有效的介紹的
I just point out that in this
我只要指出說在這個裡面
There are also stories about women disguised as men
同樣有女伴男裝的故事
and more than one
而且是不只一個
It can be said that it is a string of star conferences
可以說是一個群星大會串
That's almost all the female characters in it
就是裡面幾乎所有的女性角色
She's been through one in her life
她的人生當中都曾經經歷過一個
stage of masculinity
女伴男裝的階段
And what?
而且呢
through cross-dressing
都透過了女伴男裝
achieve a certain success
而達到了某一種成功
what about inside
那麼裡面呢
there is a first heroine
有一個第一女主角呢
called
叫做
girl
女孩
when she is a female name
當她是女性的名字的時候
Her name is Guibifang
她叫做貴弼方
when she was male
當她是男性的時候呢
Her name is Gui Hengkui
她叫做貴橫奎
anyway this one
總之這位
this this
這位這個
this expensive
這位貴
ma'am or mr.
女士或是貴先生
what about her
她呢
yes
是
The author wants to shape a past and present
作者想要塑造的一個古往今來
An image of the most remarkable woman
最傑出的女性的一個形象
so is she the best
那麼她是不是最傑出
Everyone is going to read the novel
各位要去看小說
to be able to judge
才能夠判斷
What we want to emphasize here is that
我們在這裡要強調的是
what about this woman
這個女性呢
She is because she disguised herself as a man
她正因為她女伴男裝之後呢
Whether it is literary or intellectual
不管是文智也好
Martial arts are also good
武功也好
She is a master of ancient scriptures
她都正古碩經
that's awesome
就太厲害了
How powerful is this emperor?
厲害到這個皇帝呢
take her
把她
The story is set in the Tang Dynasty
這個故事是設定在唐朝
So it's proven
所以是有繁證的
what about the emperor
那麼皇帝呢
seal her as
就把她封為
should be Guangxi
應該是廣西
sorry
對不起
because it's been a while
因為有點久了
a bit unsure
有點不太確定
In short, Yunnan and Guangxi are a big town in the southwest
雲南 廣西總之是西南部的一個一方大鎮
it is a king
它是一個繁王
to this point
是到這個地步
so what's interesting
那麼有趣的是呢
Its identity will still be revealed
它的身份還是會暴露了
when it is exposed
當它暴露以後呢
It was forced to give up its status as the king
它就被迫要放棄它的這個王的身份
it's getting married to its fiancé
它要結婚跟它的未婚夫結婚
And it has to give up his throne to its husband
而且它必須把他的王位就讓給它的丈夫
And it becomes a Queen itself
而它自己就變成一個 Queen
a queen
一個皇后
not a queen
不是 一個繁王的王后
Then of course this lady is very reluctant
那麼這個貴女士當然就很不情願
Well, there is a very interesting description in the novel that says
那麼小說有一段非常有趣的描寫說
How reluctant is he?
他不情願到什麼地步呢
He's not willing until he actually dies
他不情願到他真的就死掉
What about his true soul?
他的這個一旅真魂呢
just lightly
就輕悠飄悠悠的呢
Arrived on a fairy mountain
就到了一個仙山之上
Of course we know that in the traditional
那當然我們知道其實傳統裡面
Often there is a frame of this discount
往往有一個這個折降的這個框架
That is to say, it would have been
也就是說本來是
He is a fairy, because he committed a crime, so he was brought down to the world to walk around
是仙人,因為犯了罪,所以折降到人世來走一遭
So is this lady
這個貴女士也是這樣
After his journey of conquest of the soul arrived at Xianshan
他這個一旅征魂到了仙山之後
The owner of the fairy mountain there told him
那裡仙山的主人就告訴他說
It's not your time yet, take this pill obediently
你的時候還沒到,乖吃下這顆藥丸吧
you'll be fine
你就沒事了
sorry , two pills
對不起,兩顆藥丸吧
This pill is called... what?
這個藥丸叫做...什麼呢?
Qin Dan
叫做琴丹
Why is it called Qindan?
為什麼叫琴丹?
It means to be in the heart of this noble lady
意思就是要在這個貴女士的心中
Plant a seed that can develop the love between men and women
種下一個可以去發展男女之情的一個種子
Only in this way can he start his marriage with his husband
唯有如此他才可能開展他跟他的丈夫的婚姻
In other words, the relationship between men and women did not exist for him.
也就是說這個男女之情對他來說本來是不存在的
It is to allow him to continue his life on earth for a period of time
是為了要讓他能夠延續一段在世上的日子
So there is only one...
所以才有一個...
a divine power an external force
一個神力 一個外力
planted in his heart
種在他心中的
and it's temporary
而且是暫時的
OK good
OK 好
I think this imagination is more
我覺得這個想像比
Jueqin Valley
崛琴谷啊
what's more interesting
什麼的那個 要有趣多了
then he eats this
那麼他吃下這個
What about after this heavy sheet music?
這個重琴單之後呢
What about him? He was originally because
他呢 他本來就是因為
He vomited blood and died because he was too
吐血而亡 因為他太
Sad and angry, that's it
悲憤了 就是這個
I am the only one in this Botian industry
這個波天的工業都是我一個人
I saved up for nothing
攢下的 我居然就要平白無故
Give it to someone else and I don't love him at all
就讓給別人 而且我根本不愛他
Well this he too
那麼這個 他太
Sad and angry, so what?
悲憤了 所以呢
He has this blood clot in his chest
他的胸中有這個血塊呢
What about the condensed air of blood?
就血氣的凝制之氣呢
he passed out because of it
就他因此而昏死過去
he ate this
他吃下了這顆
What about after this heavy sheet music?
這個重琴單之後呢
His blood clot melts away
他這個血塊就化掉
melted temporarily
就暫時的化掉了
so he didn't die
所以他就沒有死
Just go back to the human world and continue to do his work
就回到人間來繼續做他的這個
queen
王后
so we can
所以我們可以
So even close blood
所以偶近先血
Exhausted, originally filled with grief and indignation
消盡氣 本來有滿腔悲憤的
At this time, it's only temporary
這個時候呢 就暫時的
got one
得到了一個
but only temporarily
但只是暫時
This novel has another very special
這個小說還有另外一個非常特殊的
It is he who writes about women's desire in a positive way
就是他正面的去寫了女性的慾望
the heroine
這個女主角
Although she has no love between men and women
她雖然沒有男女之情
Her relationship between men and women is outsider
她的男女之情是外家的
But she has another feeling
可是她卻有另外一種感情
and lust
以及情慾
object of this affection
這個感情的對象
not her husband
不是她的丈夫
But her boudoir secretly has a woman
而是她的閨中秘有女性
And of course this woman
而且當然這個女性
We're going to go back to this traditional situation again
我們要再次回到這個傳統的情境
This woman is actually her husband's second wife
這個女性其實是她的丈夫的第二個太太
Also her cousin
同時也是她的表妹
So her feelings are all pinned on
所以她的感情是全部寄託在
on this sister of hers
她的這個姊妹的身上的
So how far-fetched is this feeling?
那麼這個感情牽強到什麼地步呢
Their feelings are for each other
他們這個感情是彼此的
This cousin and this lady
這個表妹跟這個便女士
They used to be female companions in male middle school together
他們曾經一起女伴男中
What we see are two
我們看到的是兩個
beautiful great general
漂亮的不得了的大將軍
killing
在殺
fight on other fields
在他場之上 征戰
Once Miss Bea
有一次 碧小姐
Seriously injured, it looks like it won't work
深受重傷 眼看就是不行了
same with his cousin
他的表妹 同樣子
Wearing armor is the image of a male general
身上穿著盔甲 是一個男性的將軍的形象
My uncle described it
小叔就描寫道說
This cousin heard that your general
這個表妹 聽到貴將軍
dying
要死了
His heart is like a knife
他心裡面就好像刀割一樣
he vomits blood immediately
他馬上就吐血
And it's like blue blood
而且是血泳如青
call my brother
口中叫著哥哥
Because the two of them are dressed as women and men
因為他們兩個是女伴 男裝
I can't live anymore
自己也就活不下去了
Uncle said
小叔就說
Poor Suspicious Girl
可憐眾疑多情女
Xietu Qingpeng has died
邪土輕彭已喪生
This cousin was so sad that she died.
這個表妹 難過的自己就死過去了
How loving the children and sisters were
生前子妹多恩愛
Entering the ghost gate with you until death
至死相隨入鬼關
we can see this narrative
我們可以看到這個敘事
What kind of intensity should be used to describe the relationship between these two women?
用什麼樣的強度來描寫這兩個女性之間
What about this feeling?
這個感情呢
I said Dream of the Red Chamber
我就說紅樓夢啊
is still crying
是在還淚
What about the feelings in this flower dream?
這個流花夢裡面的感情呢
is blood
是還血
It will always use bright red blood
它永遠都用鮮紅的熱血
to express the relationship between the two women
來表達這兩個女性之間的
Concentration and intensity of emotion
感情的濃度以及強度
what about a scene like this
那麼像這樣的場景呢
Actually more than once
其實不止一次
to the second half of the novel
到了這個小說的後半部
Where is this heroine, this noble lady?
這個女主角這個貴小姐呢
Because of the love pill she ate
她因為吃下的重情丹
I can only save her for a while
只能夠保她一時
What about after it works?
要效過了之後呢
She can't stand this vulgar creature
她就無法忍受這個人間的俗類
so she has to leave
所以她必須要離開
So it means to die
那麼也就是要死掉的意思
what about after she died
那麼她死去之後呢
Where's her cousin?
她的這個表妹呢
no way to accept
沒有辦法接受
same she again
同樣的她又再一次
she can't live
她不能夠活下去
The novel is about this cousin
小說呢就寫說這個表妹呢
Kiss yourself with a sword
直接拿劍自吻
under the light wind like the wind
輕風下處如風急
She kisses this and wipes the neck directly
她直接吻這個抹脖子
when you put him to bed
把他扶上床去的時候
he is almost dead
他已經差不多就死了
The narrator tells us again
這個敘事者再次的告訴我們
between the two of them
他們兩個之間是
Wanlu Love
萬旅情絲
Entanglement can never be untied
糾纏是永遠解不開的
This and that heavy engine list
這跟那個重擎單
The weighted seed grows a tiny seedling
重下去的那顆種子長出小小的苗
after twenty years
過了二十年就會
It's totally different
就會歪滅是完全不一樣的
their love is
他們這個情絲是
getting tighter
越纏越緊
Then this cousin is using his blood
那麼這個表妹是用他的一槍熱血
to pay back this cousin
來回報這個表姐
give him affection
給他的感情
But he's not dead yet
不過他還沒死成
Did not die for the sake of
沒死成是為了要
describe this feeling
描寫這個感情的
deep and his
深厚以及他的
the will to repay his feelings with death
用死來報他感情的意志的
firm
堅決
So soon after
所以呢在不久之後呢
where is this cousin
這個表妹呢
she deliberately
她故意的在
a large banquet venue
一個大的宴會的場所
It's when the whole family gathers
就是全家人聚集的時候呢
He ascended he ascended one of the houses
他登高他登上家裡面的一座
tall building
高樓
opened the people around him, and then he committed suicide by jumping off the building
開了身邊的人 然後他就跳樓自殺
this time it worked
這次成功了
In the novel, he committed suicide by jumping off a building
小說就寫到他跳樓自殺
He sprinkled blood on the face
他熱血一槍迎面灑
Achievement party name is only for love
成就方名只為情
In this "Liu Hua Meng"
這個《劉花夢》裡面
We can see what he describes
我們可以看到他所描寫的情
i want to be in
我想在
I believe I haven't seen it in any other Chinese classical novels
我相信在任何其他的中國古典小說裡面沒有見過
I think if in our time
我覺得如果要在我們這個時代
Now let's talk about gay literature or same-sex relationships
現在要談同志文學或者是同性的感情
when so much attention
這麼受到大家關注的時候
such a work
這樣的一個作品
it actually has to be noticed
它其實是必須被注意到的
This is a work from around 1840 in the 19th century
這是一個十九世紀大概一八四零年左右的一個作品
it can be so strong
它就能夠以這樣的強度
so direct and so hot
這麼直接這樣的熱度
to write about same-sex relationships
去寫同性之間的感情
And it's placed under the frame of a female partner's men's clothing
而它又是放在一個女伴男裝的框架之下的
We can also see that I exceed a very large amount of time
我們也可以看到 我超出了非常多的時間
But I think you guys should let me finish, right?
但 我想各位應該會讓我講完 對不對
ok we can see
好 我們可以看看
it has some very interesting descriptions
它有一些非常有趣的描寫
Not only the intensity that just described this emotion
不僅有剛才那種描寫這個情感的這種強度
At the same time it also shows you the intensity of this lust
同時它也給你看了這個情欲的強度
We just talked about this novel
我們剛才說了這個小說呢
because it has this female companion
因為它有這個女伴男
Reverted to the design of the plot like a female
又回復成女這樣的情節的設計
So the relationship between the two heroines is in
所以這兩個女主角之間的關係是在
Women, women, men, women, among the various possibilities
女女 男女 這多種的可能性當中變換的
so let's look at this
所以我們看看這個
This description is talking about
這段描寫是在講說
Both of them are still dressed as men
他們兩個人都還扮成男性的樣子
Of course they know each other is female
當然他們彼此知道是女的
But outsiders think they are men
但是外人都以為他們是男的
so one of them
所以其中一個人呢
he is also married
他還結婚了
we'll talk later
我們待會再說
In this story of a woman disguised as a man
這個女伴男裝的故事裡面
This woman who is accompanied by a man must marry
這個伴成男性的女性一定要結婚
because if she doesn't get married
因為如果她不結婚的話
she can't hide
她沒有辦法掩飾
The fact that she is female
她是女性的這個事實
So we look here to say
所以我們看這裡就是說
one of them
其中一個呢
where is this lady
這個貴女士呢
What about the lady in men's clothing?
男裝的這個貴女士呢
just tell her cousin
就跟她的表妹說
your sister-in-law is my wife
你嫂嫂就是我太太
I went to the palace today
今天到皇宮去了
so what
所以呢
my room is empty
我房子間是空的
do you want to come
你要不要來啊
So
那麼
I treat you as
我就把你當作
I put my good brother
我就把我的好弟弟
Just treat yourself like you are a beautiful jiao'e
你就當作你是一個美麗的嬌娥
In fact, she is simply a beautiful Jiao'e
其實她根本就是一個美麗的嬌娥
what about after bed
那麼上了床之後呢
this brother this sister
這個這個哥哥這個姐姐
I don't even know how to describe her
我都不知道該該怎麼去形容她
please imagine
請各位自己想像
because of the
因為這裡面的
her game
她的遊戲
Her sex game is too complicated
她的性別的遊戲太複雜了
she just said
她就說
let me take your hat off
我幫你脫帽吧
let me take off your shoes
我幫你脫鞋吧
is it cold
冷了吧
I'll cover you with the quilt
我幫你蓋上被子
Then what
然後呢
after falling asleep
睡著了之後呢
this brother this sister
這個這個哥哥這個姐姐
He saw this sleeping
他看到沉睡當中的這個
What about this girl with a world-class face?
這個容顏蓋世的這個女孩子呢
He said he saw my brother drunk
他就說看到我弟弟喝醉了
red face
臉上紅紅的
so beautiful
真是太美了
I spread this back into me pulling my beloved brother
我這個展開背入我拉著我的心愛的弟弟
We are like a pair of mandarin ducks
我們就像一對鴛鴦一樣
hold here
握在這裡
so connected
這麼讓人聯繫啊
It's really beautiful, just like this water
真的是美得就如同這個出水
Compassion is average, right?
服容一般對不對
Flowers are not as beautiful as female genuine
花也沒有女正版美麗
Oh by the way
Oh by the way
Let me explain by the way
在這邊要順便說明一下
Both of them know that they are actually
他們兩個人都知道自己其實是
a man's fiancee
一個男人的未婚妻
they are cousins
他們是表姐妹
At the same time, he was engaged to his cousin
同時呢又跟自己的表哥訂過婚
So he said Huan Lang
所以他上面說環郎
Huan Lang is their common wedding dress
環郎就是他們共同的未婚服
He said such a beautiful person
他說這麼美麗的人啊
our maiden dress
我們那個未婚服
He hasn't touched it yet
他都還沒碰過哦
it was me first
是我先的
Ha ha ha ha
哈哈哈哈
I'm Hengkui, I stand first
我是橫奎我站先了
It's a pity, if we get married one day, I'll have to give it up to someone else.
真可惜 有一天我們結婚的話 我就要把它讓給別人
It's like Wang Wei, right?
就好像是王偉一樣 對不對
Such a beautiful person, I actually want to give it up to someone else
這麼美麗的人 我居然要讓給別人
instead of my beloved
而不是我的心愛的人了
it's a pity
這太可惜了
So we see this inside
所以我們就看到這個裡面
On the one hand, he is lust, on the other hand, he is emotion, and he is a comrade in arms
他一方面又是情慾 他一方面 他又是感情 他又是戰友
He's another competitor with men
他又是一個跟男性的競爭
There are too many layers
這裡面有太多太多的層次
It is our identity as a contemporary reader that can be imagined
是我們一個當代讀者的身份 是可以去想像的
It's fun, but time is of the essence and I have to hurry up to the bottom
很有趣 但是時間的關係 我必須要趕快進入到下面
I'm going to talk about this faster and faster.
這個呢 我就要越來越快的講了
This is the 1860s
這個已經到了1860年代了
The deduction of this era, this drama is really getting faster and faster
這個時代的推演 這個劇文真的是越來越快
After the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom War in 1861, Jiangnan was dilapidated
1861年代太平天國戰爭以後 江南殘破一片
But we have seen a work like this
但是我們卻看到這樣子的一個作品
a female author who took advantage of
一個女性的作者 他利用了
Taking advantage of the war in the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom
利用了太平天國的戰亂
because of her mother
因為她的母親呢
In the chaos of the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom?
在太平天國的亂中呢
Scared. Simply put, had a stroke.
被嚇到了 簡單說中風了
scared to have a stroke
被嚇到中風
so bedridden
所以就臥床不起
So what about this woman?
於是這位女性呢
she very conveniently
她就Very conveniently
That's great, I solemnly say
就是太好了 鄭重下懷說
Then I won't get married, I'll stay and take care of mom
那我不結婚吧 我留下來照顧媽媽
She took this opportunity to escape marriage
她就利用了這個機會逃避了婚姻
she will stay in this family forever
她就永遠就待在這個家庭
Even after her mother passed away
即使後來她的母親過世了
she is still not married
她仍就沒有結婚
But stay in this native family
而是待在這個原生家庭裡面
she has been creating all her life
她一輩子就創作
She wrote a novel called Goldfish Garden
她寫了一部小說叫做金魚園
And there is a heroine called Qian Shurong
而這裡面有一個叫做前淑容的女主角
let's see this
我們來看看這個
The same former Su-yong's inner monologue
同樣的前淑容的內心獨白
She said that my former Shurong
她說 我這個前淑容
me as a woman
我作為一個女人
I can only hug Lulu for the rest of my life
我只能擁擁露露過一世
nothing counts
什麼也不算一項的話
what is this
這算什麼呢
i don't want to live like this
我不想要這樣活
This is called walking towards the world
這個叫做往向人間走一走
I must proudly mark the name
我一定要揚眉吐氣把名標
i don't want to live
我不要活
Disillusionment is like Chengdu must leave something in the world
幻滅如同成都一定要在世上留下什麼
Then he said that there are so many high-minded people in this history
那麼他說這個歷史上也有那麼多志氣高
Talented women, I want to be like them
才幹高的女性我要跟他們一樣
I want Wan Gu Yangming
我要萬古陽明
What about such a volunteer?
那麼這樣的一個志願呢
There are also women in the novel we have seen before, right?
在我們之前看到的談這小說裡面的女性也都有對不對
but they are hard to do
但他們很難做到
isn't it
不是嗎
They all have to finally come to terms with going back to being women.
他們都最後必須要接受回到女性的身份
The fate of returning to the family's duty
回歸家庭的本份的命運
So what do we say about this
那麼這個前所我們怎麼說
The following is compared to the author's own choice
下面這個對照於作者本人的選擇
I think he's very autobiographical
我覺得他有非常高的自傳性
He said
他說
Husband loves wife, loves wife, respects, suffers from dementia and conceives daughter to fuck
夫愛妻恩敬患痴生而孕女往操之
Love, evil, evil, Xiao Nan, respect for the future
情魔孽障蕭南敬遠慮深仇日積之
With the so-called bubble talk, I fell into a pitfall
與正所謂泡影談話合去味墮入了現坑口
no sea swimming pool
無海會游池
Such a rejection of marriage
這樣一種對於婚姻的排斥
There must be factors of the whole society at that time behind it
一定有當時的整個的社會的因素在背後
Then we also mentioned
那麼同時我們也提過
This is also supported by a certain kind of religious transcendence pursuit
這個也有某一種宗教的超越的追求在背後支撐者
So on the one hand, it wants to escape from the secular society
所以它一方面是要逃開世俗的社會的
and home network
以及家庭的網絡
On the one hand, it seeks a higher
一方面它要追求一個更高的
No matter whether it is construction or spiritual, it is a kind of transcendence
不管是施工也好或者是精神上面也好的一種超越
So can it be done?
那麼做得到嗎?
In the 1860's it became doable
在1860這個時代它變成做得到了
Then in this goldfish garden
那麼在這個金魚園裡面
This heroine named Qian Shurong
這個叫做錢淑榮的女主角
She's with a woman who shares her ambitions
她就跟一個跟她有共同志向的女性
This woman is her woman who married her
這個女性就是她的跟她結婚的女人
These two people will be a man and a woman all their lives.
這兩個人就一輩子以一男一女
This kind of image has lived leisurely for a lifetime
這樣的形象過悠遊自在的過了一輩子
Before this kind of imagination, no female writer dared to think like this
這樣子的想像在這個之前是沒有女作家敢這樣想
So here we are seeing the change of the times
那麼我們在這裡就看到了這個時代的變化
The same as we just said in this story
同樣的我們剛才說在這個故事裡面
A woman who disguises herself as a man must marry
女伴男裝的人是不能不結婚的
So the point is how do you design this
所以重點就在你要怎麼樣去設計這個
A woman who marries a woman accepts the marriage
跟女人結婚的女人去接受這個婚姻
Then each author will have a different imagination
那每一個作者會有不一樣的想像
Then the setting in the goldfish garden is
那麼在金魚園裡面的設定就是
The woman she married and what she thinks
跟她結婚的這個女性跟她的想法
Almost everyone thinks that marriage is meaningless to marry a man
差不多都覺得婚姻跟男人結婚沒什麼意思
we are fine
我們這樣很好
The two of us are good friends and close friends
我們兩個人是要好的朋友歸中密友
We walk through life hand in hand like this
我們就這樣攜手走過一生
How good are the two of them?
他們兩個要好到什麼程度呢
so good that their relationship will gradually simulate
要好到他們的關係就會逐漸的模擬
or even beyond the intimacy of husband and wife
或甚至超越了夫妻的親密之情
For example, this section of Tianmian
例如田面的這一段
This is Qian Shurong, the female companion who wears men's clothing. She is on a business trip.
這個是這個錢淑蓉這個女伴男裝者她出差去了
then left her beloved lady at home
那麼留下了她心愛的夫人在家裡面
Then the lady said
那麼這個夫人她就說
Whoops I'm lying in my yard all over
哎呦我躺在我的院院整個
I miss him so much, I can't help crying when I think about talking about wolves
好想他喔 意到談狼就忍不住都掉淚了
thinking about him all night
一整個晚上都在想他
I'm like this girl who lost his partner
我就好像失去了伴侶的這個姑其之人
can't fall asleep
沒有辦法睡著
My beloved has been away for so long and has not heard from me
我的良人去了這麼久了都沒有來信
I'm really lovesick, I've lost weight
我真的是相思啊 我都瘦了
Then such an emotional description
那麼這樣的一個感情的描述
If we pull him out of his veins
如果我們把他拉離他的脈絡的話
you will feel that this is a
你就會覺得這就是一個
An ordinary display of love between husband and wife, right?
普通的夫妻之間的情愛的表現 對吧
Or let's look at the following sentences
或者是我們看下面的這幾句
This is writing about this former Shurong
這是在寫說這個前淑榮呢
he will be very flirtatious
他呢會很會調情
He will use sweet words to make his wife happy
他就會花言巧語的來哄他的夫人高興
Then the lady scolded him and said
那麼這個夫人呢就罵他說
Your girlfriend is only a year old
你女伴男裝才不過一年
you feel like this
你就覺得這個鬼樣子
this exile
這個流亡器
You are such a fool, suck this gray shoe
你這樣胡鬧啊 吸這個灰鞋呀
Joke, have you forgotten your real face?
戲虐呀 你都忘了你本來面目了嗎
What is the original face?
什麼叫做本來面目呢
You're a woman, of course.
本來面目當然就說你是個女人
good
好
but the problem is
可問題就是
If the imagination of the story says it's going to succeed
如果說這個故事的想像它要成功
That is to say
也就是說
This Qian Shurong must be able to act as a man
這個錢淑榮他要能夠以男性的身份
successfully retired
順利的當完官退休
get retired seam
拿到退休縫
And then have a good time with his wife
然後跟他的夫人悠遊自在的過癮
For the rest of his life, he must forget his true colors
一輩子他就必須要忘卻他的本來面目
How can I forget my true colors
那怎麼樣忘卻本來面目
One of the necessary conditions
其中就有一個必要條件
That is, he must be able to successfully simulate the relationship between men and women
就是他必須要能夠成功的去模擬男女之間的關係
what about this time
那在這個時候呢
Female writers will have a lot of imagination and expression of this kind of love language
女性的作家就會有非常多的這種情語的想像跟表達
that is to say
那麼也就是說
Although the matter of dressing up as a man
雖然女伴男裝這件事情
he's not though
他不是雖然
It's about dressing up as a man.
就是女伴男裝這件事情
Definitely not something you just do when you get out of the house
絕對不是一個只要走出家門才去做的事情
If you think about it, if I decide today
各位要想 如果我今天決定
I'm Meng Lijun, I'm going to dress up as a man
我是孟立軍 我要女扮男裝了
I can't wear a dress and put on lipstick at home
我不能夠在家裡面還穿著裙子插上口紅
When I went out, I hurriedly changed into men's clothes
出門的時候 才匆匆忙忙的換上男裝
Put on the boots, no, that wouldn't be a successful drag
穿上靴子 不行 那不會是一個成功的扮裝
I have to put myself through and through
我必須要徹頭徹尾的把自己
reinvented as a male
重新改造 成一個男性
From dress up to speech to behavior and even love language
從裝扮到言語 到行為 甚至到情語
have to be male
都必須要變成男性
this costume will be successful
這個扮裝才會成功
But if he succeeds, is it still a disguise?
但如果他成功的話 這還是扮裝嗎
We can see the imagination of a woman disguised as a man
我們就可以看到女扮男裝這樣的一個想像
how many layers of complexity
面他有多少複雜的層面
He's about what's called humanity, what's called gender
他關係到所謂的人性 所謂的性別
Identity, the nature of gender, erotic relationships, etc.
認同 性別的本質 情愛的關係等等
Some of these introspections are ours until today
這一些的反省都是我們直到今天
I'm afraid they're all still tangled up with complex issues
恐怕都仍舊纏擾不清的複雜的問題
i am a greedy person
我是個貪心的人
So I always hope that in a speech
所以我總是希望在一個演講裡面
Try to share as much as possible with my audience
盡量的跟我的聽眾們分享更多的東西
so please give me two more minutes
所以請再給我兩分鐘
This is also a work from the late 19th century.
這也是一個19世紀很後期的一個作品
It is a post-Taiping work
是太平天過以後的作品
This work is called Zi Xu Ji
這個作品叫做子虛記
The title of this work gives us a very...
這個作品的名字給我們一種很...
how to say?
怎麼說呢?
This is very hypocritical, isn't it?
這個很子虛吧?子虛屋友嘛
It's all just imagination, don't take it seriously
就是全部都是想像不要當真這樣的一個意思
But what?
可是呢
This novel also resolutely demonstrates
這一個小說它同樣的是堅決的展現了
the female writer
這個女作家
He wants to imagine a story about a woman who refuses to look back
他要想像一個女性不肯回頭的一個故事
This is a manuscript written by Zixu
這個是子虛記的一個稿本
Well, Zixu Ji actually has a quite moving story.
那麼子虛記其實有一個相當動人的故事
This is Wang Ou rewarding him after writing Zixu Ji
就是這個汪偶賞他寫完子虛記之後
This manuscript was inherited by his daughter
這個稿本是由他的女兒繼承的
Then after the daughter inherits
那麼女兒繼承了之後
When I brought it to my husband's house, his husband's...
帶到夫家就由他夫家的...
Women's Literature is Herself
女性文就是她自己
then her daughter
然后她的女儿
her daughter's daughter
她的女儿的女儿
female inheritance
就是有女性继承
So she's totally an heir to a woman
所以她完全是一个女性的一个继承物
She and everything else have male inheritance
她跟别的东西都是有男性继承
are different
是不一样的
then the impressive thing is
那么令人感动的就是
This thing has been around since the 1860s
这个东西从1860年代一直
passed the test of time
通过时代的考验
During the Cultural Revolution in the 1960s
一直到1960年代的文化大革命期间
women in this house
这家的女性
descendants of this author
这个作者的后代
are risking their lives
都冒着生命的危险
to protect the high book
去保护了这个高本
they didn't give it up
他们没有放弃它
You have to imagine something like this
各位要想象这样的一个东西
If it was discovered at the time
如果在当时是被发现的话
what a disaster it could be to that family
可能给那家人带来多么大的灾难
But this family has worked hard to preserve this high capital.
可是这家人他们就是努力的保全了这个高本
Then probably a few years ago
那么大概就是前几年
donate money to this
把财捐出来给这个
Probably to the local provincial or municipal government or something
可能是给当地的省政府或市政府之类的
So behind this story is actually
那么这个故事背后其实
The story behind the preservation of this text
这个文本的保存的故事的背后
Actually it is
其实就是
Just witnessed a talk about this novel
就是見證了一個談此小說
How it's possible to be a soul treasure passed down from generation to generation by women
如何可能成為女性代代相傳的一種心靈的寶物
such a background
這樣的一個背景
good
好
sorry i didn't write it down
對不起 我沒有寫下來
Okay, it's okay, I read it well again
好 沒關係 我又念的好了
So what's in this subtitle?
那麼這個子虛記裡面呢
his heroine begins by saying
他的女主角一開始就說
I want red bayberry to be a man
我要楊梅土氣做男子
And I'm definitely not going back as a woman
而且我絕對不會恢復女性的身份
If one day I'm exposed
如果有一天我被揭穿的話
i will die
我就死
so in this story
那麼在這個故事裡面呢
What about the heroine?
真的這個女主角呢
in the end
到最後呢
he died
他就是以死名制
He absolutely refuses to follow the norms of society.
他絕對不肯要按照社會的規範來走
So we can probably see
所以我們大概可以看到
This Zixuji is similar to the era of Jin Yuyuan just now
這個子虛記跟剛才那個金語元的時代差不多
They all manifested a new, absolute will
他們都顯現出了一種新的 絕絕的意志
The will to break social norms
衝破社會規範的意志
But what?
可是呢
They imagined the consequences differently
他們對於這個後果的想像不太一樣
Jin Yuyuan's practice
金語元的做法
More optimistic, he imagined a successful companion
比較樂觀他想像了一個成功的伴裝
And the author of this memoir
而這個子虛記的作者
imagined a woman
則是想像了一個女性
the pursuit of this life
對於這個生命的追求
In the end there will be no way to resist the system
到最後會沒有辦法抵抗體制
But you must use your own life to live and die
但是必須用自己的生命來生死與遜
such a design
這樣的一種設計
So this one is from the 1860s onwards
所以這個是1860年代以後
two different reactions
兩種不同的反應
Well, finally, it's time to come to the conclusion.
好 最後終於要來到結論了
So soon I will share with you a little
那麼很快的我跟大家稍微分享一下
I am about female elastic magnetic novel
我對於女性彈磁小說
Some understanding of this creative form
這個創作形式的一些理解
The first one is the female elastic magnetic novel
第一個就是女性彈磁小說
it's very autobiographical
它有非常高的自傳性
because these women writers
因為這些女作家
they are holding
他們都是懷抱著
Refusing to let myself follow the disillusionment of the flesh
不肯讓自己隨著肉體的幻滅
creative consciousness
而消失的一種創作的自覺
They hope that they can achieve immortality
他們是希望自己可以達到不朽
So this creative consciousness
所以這種創作的自覺
will keep them in their texts
會讓他們不斷的在他們的文本裡面
to show yourself
去展現自己
These little books, although they imagined a lot of strange stories about relatives
是这些小书呢 它虽然想象了很多亲戚百怪的故事
But it will also write a lot of daily life related to women
但是它同样会写很多跟女性相关的日常生活
For example, eating, for example, giving gifts
比方说吃饭啦 比方说送礼啦
For example, production, etc.
比方说生产啦 等等
So many women's unique experiences
那么很多女性独有的经验
The third one is like Li Qingzhao, who doesn’t just write about personal emotions
第三个呢 就如同李清照 不是只写个人情感
Also write the same as the master of the country
也写家国大师一样
What about these female authors, they don’t just write about the emotions in this regulation
这些女性作者呢 他们也不是只写这个规中感情
They will put their novels in a big historical framework
他们呢 都会把他们的小说呢 放在一个大的历史的框架里面
They like to think of writing novels as writing history.
他们很喜欢把自己写小说这件事情当作说是写史
is a reflection on history
是一种对历史的反思
Well even we didn't have that example today
那么甚至 我们今天没有举到那个例子
But there are some novels, it's just that I want to rewrite the famous history
但是有一些小说呢 完全就是抱着一个我要重写名史
Such a will is writing
这样子的一个意志在写的
So what next we can see
那么接下来呢 我们可以看到
From the example of Liu Huameng just now
从刚才刘花梦的例子里面
We can see that this female writer
我们可以看到 这个女性的作家呢
talk about this novel
可以利用谈此小说
It is said that this relatively flexible genre expresses very strongly
說這個比較有彈性的文類去表達非常強烈
But in the genre of poetry
而是在詩詞這些文類裡面
feelings that cannot be expressed
沒有辦法表達的感情
same-sex love
例如同性之愛
So in the end we
那麼最後呢我們
In the end, it's actually a question
最後呢其實是一個這個問題
That is, from these many works
也就是從這許許多的作品裡面
we can really explore
我們真的可以好好地去探索
these women writers
這些女作家
social norms
他們跟社會規範
relationship with the so-called system
跟所謂的體制之間的關係
Of course they resist
他們當然是抗拒的
Of course they are counterbalanced
他們是當然是抗衡的
But they often have to be dewormed too
但是他們往往也必須要驅蟲
So in the twentieth or twenty-first century
所以在二十世紀或二十一世紀
when we re-read these novels
我們重看這些小說的時候呢
Never simply
千萬不能夠單純地以
is this feminism
這個是不是女性主義
or is it a revolution
或者是不是一種革命
Is this a gender revolution
這是不是一種性別的革命
such a single thought
這樣的單一的想法
look at these works
來看這些作品
ok let's skip this
好這個我們跳過吧
Finally, as a New Year's gift for everyone today
最後作為今天給大家的新年禮物
I want everyone to appreciate
我想讓大家欣賞
two minutes this is contemporary
兩分鐘的這個是當代
very famous
非常有名的
Real erotic fisting of an actress
真正的色役雙拳的一位女演員
Ms. Sheng Xiaojun's performance
盛曉筠女士的演出
This is Mulan Ci
這是木蘭詞
everyone will recite
是大家都會背的
Let's see Mulan Ci
我們看看木蘭詞
If you use Peng Xi to perform
如果用彭席演出的話
what is called
什麼叫做
and look at the age is you not the day
与看歲 是你 不當天
Thank you very much Chief Hu for his speech today
非常謝謝胡首長今天給我們的演講
I believe you enjoyed an evening of literary fiction sounds as much as I did
我相信各位跟我一樣是享受了一個晚上的文學小說的聲音
Not only he is greedy, but I am also greedy
不只他很貪心 我也很貪心
I've been wanting to hear it all
我就一直想要聽完
Based on my usual experience in hosting meetings
以我平常主持會議的經驗
I interrupted him about half an hour ago.
我大概半個小時前就打斷他了
I can't bear to interrupt him today.
今天是非常不忍心打斷他
Especially for me, someone with a background in science, engineering and mathematics
尤其對我 像我這個是理工數學背景的人來講
This opportunity to enjoy the voice of this spa novel
這個機會享受這個溫泉小說的聲音
So sorry and don't really have much time
所以也抱歉也沒有實際太多的時間
Let me ask you this question
給各位貴賓這個問問題
I think unless you are very interested in this stuff
我想除非你是對這個東西非常有興趣的
I guess just open up a question or two
我想就開放一兩個問題吧
ok please
好請問
ask the professor
請教教授
the one just mentioned
那個剛剛提到的那個
That is to say, a woman disguised as a man became a high official
就是說女扮男裝當了大官
So during tutoring, will you commit the crime of the Seventh Army?
那在補習的時候是會犯下七軍大罪嗎
Yes Nadine Minger asks you
對 那丁明格問你
That is to say, these protagonists, they all
就是說他們這些主角他們都
I want to make myself a boy
一心一意的要把自己辦成男生
right
對不對
Then I was wondering if they were modern people
那我在想如果換成他們是現代的人
then they should be
那他們應該會是
like we are very transgender now
像我們現在是非常有的變性的
right
對不對
the rule is
那定則就是
And the same-sex business, right?
還有那個同性業務對不對
Thanks
謝謝
thanks for your question
謝謝您的問題
yes
沒錯
Disguising a woman as a man is called reversing yin and yang, which is a crime of deceiving the emperor
女伴男裝這個叫顛倒陰陽是欺君大罪
His crime is not just because of bullying the king
他的罪不只是因為欺君
At the same time, it is also because he disturbed the order of heaven and earth
同時也是因為他錯亂了天地的秩序
so it's really a felony
所以這確實是重罪
It is precisely because of this
也正是因為如此
So the heroine in this novel
所以這個小說裡面的這個女主角
They will all be under a lot of pressure
他們都會面臨非常大的壓力
Like why in the story of Meng Lijun
像為什麼孟立軍的故事裡面
the emperor can oppress him saying
皇帝可以壓迫他說
Come on and develop this affair with me a little bit
你來跟我發展一點這個婚外情
Just because the emperor can grab him by the throat
就是因為皇帝可以掐住他的喉嚨
right
對不對
I just want to expose you
我只要揭發你
you are capital crime
你就是死罪
I can't spare you
我饒不了你
So in that story is
所以在那個故事裡面的是
The queen mother came forward and said to forgive him.
太后出面去說饒了他吧
So so indeed this is a key point
那麼所以確實這是一個關鍵點
All this related text inside
所有的這個相關的文本裡面
will ponder over this issue.
都會在這個問題上面琢磨的
Each author has his own interpretation
每一個作者有自己不同的解釋法
like the one we just saw
像我們剛才看到的那個
The story of the former Shurong
那個前淑榮的故事
he is not
他不就是
Instead of Qian Shurong
而不是前淑榮
another one
另外一個
The story of Zixu
子虛記的那個故事
won't he die
他不就死嗎
it's me who dies
就是我死吧
good
好
then as for
那麼至於
Yun’s second question just now is about their
雲剛才第二個問題就是說他們
Are we going to treat them as transgender in modern times?
放到當代我們是不是要把他們當作變性者
Or maybe this can't be called a transsexual?
或者是這個不能叫做變性者吧
what is it called
這叫什麼呀
not just gay
也不只是同性戀
should have a proper name
應該叫做有專有的名字
I dare not now
我現在不敢
A question of gender identity
性別認同的一個問題
it's a very complex question
這是一個非常複雜的問題
It is also different in each text
在每個文本裡面也都不太一樣
I personally feel like Liu Huameng
我個人的感覺像劉花夢
or a goldfish garden
或者是金魚園
author of goldfish garden
金魚園的作者
Exhibits very strong celibacy
表現出非常強烈的獨身主義
the need not to marry
不婚的這種需求
But what about his celibacy
但是呢他的這個獨身主義
Does it have anything to do with his gender identity?
是否跟他的性別認同有關係
It's more ambiguous, not so clear
是比較曖昧的 沒有那麼清楚
We can see that he certainly describes
我們可以看到他當然描寫了
His so-called wife who is also female
他的這個同樣是女性的這個所謂的夫人
this is living a good married life
這個過著很好的婚姻生活
but in the novel
但是在小說裡面
you don't feel very
你並不會感受到非常
strong desire
強烈的慾望
Lust Carnal desire Rarely
情慾 肉體的慾望 很少
But Liu Huameng's work is different
但是劉花夢那個作品就不太一樣了
I think Liu Huameng's work
我覺得劉花夢那個作品
what is conveyed in
裡面所傳達出來的
this homosexual
這個同性情感的
intensity depth etc.
強度 深度 等等
cannot be ignored
是不可忽視的
That is to say, we can't simply say
就是說我們沒有辦法單純的只是說
This is the intimacy between girls
這就是女孩子之間親密的
Are you afraid of handing in? What? No.
手怕交嗎?什麼?不是的
if we face it honestly
如果我們誠實的去面對
words in that text
那個文本的話
we will know
我們會清楚的知道
that is gay
那個是同性戀
But does that mean
但是呢 那個是不是就表示
He has a problem with his gender identity
他的性別認同有問題
i think that's something else
我覺得那是另外一回事
because homosexuality does not mean
因為同性戀並不表示
His gender identity is different
他的性別認同是不一樣的
right?
對不對?是吧
So I think that should be discussed separately
所以我覺得那個是要分開來談
But in these works
但是呢 在這些作品裡面
is there any author
有沒有任何一個作者
The writer moved to modern times alone
作家 同樣一個人搬到現代
He'll say I'm going transgender
他會說我要去變性
I dare not say I think it is possible
我不敢說 我覺得有可能
But I can't see it from the text
但是我沒有辦法從文本裡面看到
very clear evidence
非常明確的證據
Well, I think because of time
好 我想因為時間的關係
we probably can't help it
我們大概也沒辦法
Today I am really grateful to Chief Hu
今天真的是非常感謝胡首長
his greedy novel
他這個貪止小說
Not his deep interpretation
不是他這種深刻的詮釋
we probably don't understand
我們大概都不懂
I think I probably know and understand a little
我想我大概知道聽得懂一點皮毛
Maybe the women here can understand more deeply
說不定在座的女性是能夠體會更深
At least knowing I can have something to watch when I retire
至少知道我以後退休可以有東西可以看
Thank you again Chief Hu Thank you
再次的謝謝胡首長 謝謝